<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Essayes of anatomy in which the construction of the organs and their mechanical operations are clearly explained according to the new hypotheses / by ******, Dr. in Medicine, written originally in French.</title>
            <title>Essais d'anatomie. English</title>
            <author>Beddevole, Dominique, d. ca. 1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4019</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11955786</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11955786</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51501</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27239)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51501)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 54:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Essayes of anatomy in which the construction of the organs and their mechanical operations are clearly explained according to the new hypotheses / by ******, Dr. in Medicine, written originally in French.</title>
                  <title>Essais d'anatomie. English</title>
                  <author>Beddevole, Dominique, d. ca. 1692.</author>
                  <author>Scougall, J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 184 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Mosman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Essais d'anatomie.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Dominique Beddevole. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Translated by J. Scougall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Chicago Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Human anatomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51501:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51501:1"/>
            <p>ESSAYES OF ANATOMY In which the Conſtruction of the ORGANS AND THEIR MECHANICAL OPERATIONS. Are clearly Explained according to the new HYPOTHESES.</p>
            <p>By * * * * * * Dr. in Medicine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written Originally in</hi> French.</p>
            <p>EDINBURGH, Printed by <hi>George Moſman,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop in the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Cloſe, Anno Domini</hi> 1691</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51501:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51501:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE The VISCOUNT of TARBET.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He following Treatiſe receiving the Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of a moſt Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Peice, it has encouraged the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and publiſhing this Tranſlation, to ſupply the ſcarcity of <hi>French</hi> Copies, and to ſatisfy the Curious, who do not underſtand that Language. And becauſe the Author of the <hi>Eſſayes</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:51501:3"/> has both the Honour of Your Lordſhips Acquaintance, and alſo the Favour of Your good Opinion: Therefore Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Patronage and Protection, is Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſired to this Tranſlation, which will be found a juſt enough Repreſentation of the Author Thoughts and Sentiments. And the Publiſher hath preſumed to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix Your Lordſhips Name to this, that He may teſtify his Duty to Your Lordſhip; and likewiſe becauſe of Your Lordſhips readineſs to encourage all Ingenious Studies and Enterpriſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:51501:3"/>
            <head>The STATIONERS ADVERTISMENT TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THoſe who Judge of a Book by the Title, are Diſcouraged when a Title is Simple; and on the contrary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that a Work is Excellent, when Men have the Art to give a great <hi>Idaea</hi> of it, by an ingeniouſly invented Title; we might doubt of their acceptance of this little Treatiſe, if many others which have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared with the ſame Modeſty, and have nevertheleſs had a great Succeſs, had not favourably diſpoſed the Reader for the word <hi>Eſſayes.</hi> Since thoſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Montaigne,</hi> how many others have appeared in <hi>Phyſick</hi> and in <hi>Morality,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:51501:4"/> which have been the Admiration of all the Learned? I hope therefore that they will not be prejudiced againſt this preſent Treatiſe, becauſe it promiſeth nothing but <hi>Eſſayes,</hi> and that they will have the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to ſee what it ſayes. After which I am perſwaded they will be ſatisfied. I ſhall ſay no more to recommend my Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:51501:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THe knowledge of the <hi>Living Body</hi> is extremly neceſſary for <hi>Phyſicians.</hi> Without it they do nothing but at adventure. This is a <hi>Flambeau</hi> which gives them <hi>Light</hi> in the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and in the <hi>Choice of Remedies.</hi> And all they who underſtand nothing in it, can be reaſonably concluded no other then <hi>Charletons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt part of <hi>Judicious</hi> and <hi>Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men</hi> have alwayes acknowledged this <hi>Truth.</hi> It is for this that they have ever cultivated <hi>Anatomy</hi> with much applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In the paſt <hi>Ages</hi> they thought they knew all that could be <hi>Learned</hi> of it. And
<pb facs="tcp:51501:5"/> in this, they have found, to the ſhame of <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> that they have made but a very ſmall advance in this <hi>Science.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The preoccupation in which they were in paſt Ages in favour of the <hi>Antients,</hi> was the Cauſe why they did not apply themſelves to Learn but what theſe had diſcovered. <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> only were then ſtudied. They ſought in their <hi>Writings,</hi> all that they were obliged to know to render; them <hi>Learned Men.</hi> They imagin'd they knew all, and took thoſe for <hi>Viſionairs,</hi> who pretended to know more than theſe. Thus the paſt <hi>Ages</hi> have been extreamely barren in <hi>Diſcoveries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Thanks to the <hi>Penetration</hi> of an excellent <hi>Philoſopher</hi> of this Age, it has been diſcovered that the <hi>Living Body</hi> is nothing but a <hi>Machine.</hi> Men have applied their Minds to diſcover its <hi>Springs.</hi> In this <hi>Harvey</hi> and <hi>Pecquet</hi> have been ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful. The <hi>Circulation of the Blood</hi> has Immortaliz'd the one, and the <hi>Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatory</hi> of the <hi>Chyle</hi> and the <hi>Thoracick
<pb facs="tcp:51501:5"/> Conduit,</hi> has given the other a <hi>Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which will never end.</p>
            <p>Their Example has animated all the <hi>Anatomiſts.</hi> They found they had made ſmall progreſs in the knowledge of this <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine.</hi> They were perſwaded that they needed but ſearch to make <hi>Diſcoveries.</hi> In effect the <hi>Bartholin</hi>'s, the <hi>Wharton</hi>'s, the <hi>Steno</hi>'s, the <hi>Willis</hi>'s, the <hi>Gliſſon</hi>'s, the <hi>Lower</hi>'s, the <hi>des Graaf</hi>'s, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And above all the <hi>Malphigis</hi> have ſearched very deep into the <hi>Structure</hi> of the <hi>Living Body.</hi> The <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> which they have made do give us an <hi>Idaea</hi> of an <hi>Animal,</hi> altogether different from what the <hi>Antients</hi> had of it.</p>
            <p>It might ſeem that after them, there remained nothing to be <hi>Diſcovered.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs there are <hi>Treatiſes</hi> frequently publiſhed, which contain ſome new thing, and I doubt not but an hundred years hence they may make ſome new <hi>Diſcovery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Contrivance</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for explaining the <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of its <hi>Parts;</hi> and if what we fancy to to be the <hi>Contrivance,</hi> is not ſufficient for
<pb facs="tcp:51501:6"/> the Explication of the <hi>Operations</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> nor the <hi>Effects</hi> of its <hi>Particular Members</hi> and <hi>Parts</hi> we may therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that there is ſomething of this <hi>Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance</hi> yet to be <hi>Diſcovered.</hi> The beſt <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomiſts</hi> do ingenuouſly acknowledge, that they fail in many <hi>Particulars;</hi> there are therefore many <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> yet to be made.</p>
            <p>Some of them will be found in theſe <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſays;</hi> and to me they ſeem <hi>Important</hi> enough to make me believe that they will not be unacceptable. I do not conceive the ſame hopes of my <hi>Sentiments,</hi> concerning the nature and uſe of the <hi>Liquors</hi> which are found in the <hi>Living Body.</hi> To thoſe who are prejudiced, the Novelty of the moſt part of them, will make them ſeem extravagant. But I hope thoſe who do not condemn an Opinion, without having examined it, will do me the favour to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that if they find them Erroneous, I was not haſtily miſtaken without good and probable inducements.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only beg of them to Read the firſt <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of theſe <hi>Eſſays,</hi> before they read
<pb facs="tcp:51501:6"/> the reſt. It gives the <hi>Idaea</hi> which I make to my ſelf of the <hi>Elements,</hi> and without it, they will not conceive ſo diſtinctly what is contain'd in the reſt.</p>
            <p>There is a great Connexion between all the <hi>Treatiſes</hi> of theſe <hi>Eſſays:</hi> Thoſe who would underſtand them well, will not do ill to read them in Order. The Order which I give them will ſeem Fantaſtical to thoſe who are accuſtomed to read Courſes of <hi>Anatomy</hi> written according to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Method. But they who ſhall obſerve that each <hi>Treatiſe</hi> ſerveth for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of that which followeth, will acknowledge that I have given them a <hi>Natural Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps it may be thought ſtrange, that I make no mention of <hi>Authors</hi> in the places where I ſet down their <hi>Diſcoveries.</hi> They may even think that I do it on Deſign, to attribute to my ſelf the Glory of them. In this they would do me a great Injury. <hi>I</hi> am not ſo baſe as to acquire Reputation at the Expence of that of others. But <hi>I</hi> have not nam'd thoſe who have made the <hi>Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:51501:7"/> becauſe every Body knows them and it would ſerve nothing for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of theſe <hi>Eſſays.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is an excellent <hi>Anatomiſt</hi> at <hi>Montpellier,</hi> who is called Monſieur <hi>Chirac.</hi> The firſt reaſon which has made me wave the Names of others, has no place as to him. Nevertheleſs, I have not Nam'd him any where. But I'le do him Juſtice here. It is he who has written to me, that all the <hi>Glandules</hi> were nothing but heaps of <hi>Circumvolutions of Veſſels;</hi> after which I have told him. <hi>That by chance I have obſerved ſomething like to this in the Proſtates of a Dog.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover almoſt all Authors do place their Names at the Frontiſpiece of their Works. This probably flows from the good Opinion that every one has of his own <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions.</hi> Every Body is fond of them. There is ſcarce a ſilly <hi>Scribler,</hi> who does not imagine that his Work has ſomething of Tranſcendent in it. Though for the moſt part it is nothing but a Multilation of good <hi>Authors.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51501:7"/>
            <p>By this you may know the reaſon why I do not as others. I have not a good enough Opinion of this Work to imagine that it will do me a great Honour. Beſides I Write but to expoſe my <hi>Thoughts</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to the end, that if they be wrong, they may Correct them, and if they be juſt, they may help forward to better.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:51501:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51501:8"/>
            <head>ESSAYS OF ANATOMY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="discourse">
               <head>
                  <hi>The firſt Diſcourſe.</hi> Of the Elements of a Living Body.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Of the firſt Elements.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Idea</hi> that we have of Matter and Motion, leads us to think, that all Bodies are compoſed of Inſenſible <hi>Corpuſcles,</hi> of different Magnitude and Figure If it fall out that many of theſe <hi>Corpuſcles</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:51501:9"/> are united, they compoſe little Maſſes, which we call <hi>Molecules.</hi> And if they continue ſeparated from one another, by reaſon of great Agitation, they compoſe a Matter which we ſhall call the <hi>Aethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Matter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereas the <hi>Molecules</hi> are formed by the aſſemblage of parts of the <hi>Aethereal Matter;</hi> there is amongſt them an almoſt infinite diverſity, as well in reſpect of their Magnitude as their Structure and Figure. This will be evident enough to thoſe who ſhall conſider, that the parts of the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereal Matter</hi> are very different from one another. It is for this that the <hi>Molecules,</hi> which are made up of them, have great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity amongſt them. And ſince we have no reaſon to deny, but that they are of as many ſorts as can be, we may well think that they differ amongſt themſelves an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of wayes, as well in reſpect of their Magnitude, as of their Structure and their Figure.</p>
                  <p>To examine well the differences of their Structure and Figure, all the <hi>Molecules,</hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51501:9"/> may be conveniently reduced to five kinds. The firſt ſhall be of thoſe which have <hi>ſharp Angles</hi> on their Surface with much Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity. We ſhall call theſe kinds of <hi>Mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules, Acides.</hi> The ſecond ſhall be of thoſe which have many Pores, great and open. Theſe we ſhall name <hi>Alcalis.</hi> The third ſhall be of thoſe which are branched, we ſhall call them <hi>Sulphurs.</hi> The fourth ſhall be of thoſe which are long, and their Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities like thoſe of an Oval. We ſhall name them <hi>Phlegme.</hi> And in fine, the fifth ſhall be of thoſe, which have not ſharp Angles on their Surface, which are not very Potous, which are not branched, and which are not Cylindrical with Oval ends; but which are either round, or Oval, or rough, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and we call them <hi>Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Aethereal Matter</hi> flowes without ceaſing through the Pores of the <hi>Molecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> it fills alſo all the ſpaces where there are no <hi>Molecules.</hi> And the <hi>Molecules</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all the Bodies which we call <hi>Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A living Body is one of theſe Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51501:10"/> Bodies which are compoſed of <hi>Molecules.</hi> Therefore <hi>Acids, Alcalis, Sulphurs, Phlegme</hi> or <hi>Earth</hi> muſt needs be in it. Being therefore that we have propoſed to give a clear <hi>Idea</hi> of its Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this Diſcourſe, we ſhall examine the nature of <hi>Acids, Alcalis, Sulphurs, Phlegme</hi> and of <hi>Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. <hi>Of Acids.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO underſtand well the Nature of <hi>Acids,</hi> we muſt examine their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, their Stature, and their Magnitude. As to their Figure, when I examine the matter nearly, I remark that there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them almoſt an infinite difference. There are Conical, Triangular, Regular and Irregular of all ſorts: There are of them whoſe Angles are very ſharp, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of them whoſe Angles are leſs ſharp. There are who have many Angles, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who have fewer. And ſince there may be amongſt all this an Infinity of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51501:10"/> Modifications, we make no ſcruple to ſay, that there is almoſt an infinite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference amongſt <hi>Acids,</hi> by reaſon of their Figure; Which makes me think, that it would be a fruitleſs labour to endeavour to know all the differences which are amongſt the <hi>Acids,</hi> by reaſon of their Figure The multitude of them being Infinite, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hope to know them all. We ſhall therefore content our ſelves to know in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, that all the <hi>Acids</hi> have ſharp Angles on their Surface, without enquiring whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Spirit of Sulphur, for example, has its parts Conical, Pyramidal, of many ſides, or otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p>As to the Structure of <hi>Acids;</hi> foraſmuch as it conſiſts in the ranging of the Particles of the <hi>Aetherial Matter,</hi> we need not doubt but that the diverſity which is amongſt them in this reſpect, is almoſt Infinite. In effect, the ranging of theſe Particles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon their Magnitude, as well as on their Figure and their Motion.</p>
                  <p>Now there is an Infinite difference in the Magnitude and Figure of the parts of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51501:11"/> 
                     <hi>Aetherial Matter,</hi> and they move an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of wayes. There muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be an Infinite difference in the Structure of <hi>Acids.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs, foraſmuch as hardneſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the Structure, becauſe the more hard a Body is, it has the fewer Pores, or its Pores are the ſmaller, we may ſuppoſe that we know in general the Structure of all <hi>Acids;</hi> in that they being the hardeſt of all the <hi>Molecules,</hi> they muſt have the feweſt Pores, or at leaſt ſuch as are the ſmalleſt. It ſhall ſatisfy us to know this, without troubling our ſelves to no purpoſe, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover all the Modifications which may be in the Pores of <hi>Acids.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to the Magnitude of their parts, the difference is alſo infinite; ſo that to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them in this reſpect, it is impoſſible to determine all the differences. If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in the mean time, that we find <hi>Acids</hi> whoſe parts are ſo ſubtil and ſo delicate that they are exhaled by a ſmall Fire; as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the parts of the Spirit of <hi>Venus,</hi> whilſt we find others ſo groſs and Maſſy,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51501:11"/> that they do not exhale but by the force of a vehement heat, ſuch as the Oyl of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol,</hi> the Spirit of <hi>Allum,</hi> &amp;c. We may well reduce, by this means, the <hi>Acids</hi> under two kinds, by dividing them into <hi>Fixt</hi> and <hi>Volatile.</hi> The <hi>Fixt,</hi> are thoſe which do not exhale, but by the force of a vehement Fire, and the <hi>Volatiles</hi> on the contrary ſhall be thoſe which exhale by a moderate heat.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III. <hi>Of Alcalis.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SInce <hi>Alcalis</hi> are nothing but the moſt porous <hi>Molecules,</hi> to know them well, we need only examine their Figure, their Pores and their Magnitude.</p>
                  <p>We may ſay here of <hi>Alcalis,</hi> what we have ſaid of <hi>Acids</hi> in ſpeaking of their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, <hi>viz.</hi> That they are ſo many, that it is impoſſible to know them all The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, that their compoſition depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the motion of the Particles of the <hi>Aethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Matter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For ſince theſe Particles move every
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51501:12"/> way, they may in uniting themſelves com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Molecules</hi> of all ſorts of Figure, as well Regular as Irregular. So that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, finding its ſelf unable to examine them all, and wanting moreover means to accompliſh it, muſt content its ſelf to know that there are <hi>Alcalis</hi> of all ſorts of Figure, without being anxious for the Figure of each <hi>Alcali.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is good notwithſtanding to remark here that ſome <hi>Alcalis</hi> have the Figure of <hi>Acids,</hi> that is, that many <hi>Alcalis</hi> have ſharp Angles on their Surface. But becauſe they have not Solidity, they do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame effect. In ſpeaking of the hardneſs of <hi>Acids,</hi> we have inſinuated that it depends upon the ſmall number or ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Pores. Seing then the <hi>Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> are incomparably more Porous then the <hi>Acids,</hi> they muſt of neceſſity have very little hardneſs in compariſon of the other, ſo that if ſome <hi>Molecules</hi> partake of an <hi>Acid</hi> becauſe of their ſharp Angles, and of an <hi>Alcali,</hi> becauſe of the great number and wideneſs of their Pores, they cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51501:12"/> the ſame effect which <hi>Acids</hi> produce, becauſe they have no ſolidity, and in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rencounters they have not the effect of <hi>Alcalis,</hi> becauſe of the ſharp Angles of their Surface. We ſhall call theſe ſorts of <hi>Mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules, Alcaline Acide</hi> Particles.</p>
                  <p>The Pores of <hi>Alcalis</hi> are alſo different from one another an infinite number of wayes, which is the cauſe we cannot deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them; from hence it comes, that not being able to know in particular the Structure of the Pores of <hi>Alcalis,</hi> we ſhall content our ſelves to ſay, that they have the wideneſs and Figure that is needful to produce ſuch an effect, when we are to ſpeak of a Phaenomenon that depends upon them, which will ſerve on the like occaſions</p>
                  <p>As to the Magnitude of the <hi>Alcaline parts,</hi> tho' the diverſities that are amongſt them be infinite, yet we ſhall divide them into Fixt and Volatile as we have done the <hi>Acids.</hi> With this exception, that the <hi>Fixt Acids</hi> do exhale by the action of a great Fire, whereas the <hi>Fixt Alcalis</hi> do not exhale at all.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51501:13"/>
                  <p>We diſtinguiſh therefore <hi>Alcalis</hi> int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Fixt</hi> and <hi>Volatile;</hi> the <hi>Fixt</hi> are thoſe which ſubſiſt in the Fire, and change rather into Glaſs, than exhale. And the <hi>Volatile</hi> are thoſe which exhale by a moderate Fire; as for ex the Spir of Sal. Arm. the Volatile Alcals of Harts-horn.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Of the mixture of <hi>Acids</hi> with <hi>Alcalis.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AFter having treated of the <hi>Acid</hi> and <hi>Alcalis,</hi> we muſt mingle them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to ſee what will follow; and that we may follow a method that needs not be quarrelled, we ſhall ſay nothing in this Chapter, which does not follow from what has been ſaid in the foregoing.</p>
                  <p>If we conſider that a pure <hi>Alcali</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of nothing but the moſt <hi>porous Mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,</hi> it muſt needs be granted that a great deal of the <hi>Aetherial matter</hi> paſſes through the pores of its parts.</p>
                  <p>From hence it follows, that to the end a Body may ſubſiſt for a long time in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51501:13"/> torrent of the <hi>Aetherial matter,</hi> the pores which are on its Surface muſt be no greater than thoſe which are in the middle. The reaſon is, that if the pores of the Surface were not a little near equal, the parts of the <hi>Aetherial matter,</hi> which ſhould enter on one ſide, could not get out on the other with the ſame freedom as they entered. They would therefore force by their great agitation all that ſhould oppoſe their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and conſequently break the union of the parts; the aſſemblage of which did make the pores too ſmall to permit them to paſs through them Here recourſe cannot be had to the groſſer parts of the <hi>Aetherial matter,</hi> which remaining on the surface of the Body might keep its parts united, by reſiſting them uniformly with as much force as the <hi>Aetherial matter</hi> that paſſes within: Becauſe all the parts of the <hi>Aethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial matter</hi> which are leſs groſs than what runs through the parts of the Body, do not enter, and conſequently reſt on the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. But in as much as they have leſs force than what is within, they are obliged
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51501:14"/> to give way, and let them at this place make all kind of havock, by diſordering all the parts of that Body, and breaking wholly the union of it. So that in that place where the Pores are narrower than in the reſt, there will never fail to follow a diſſolution of the parts</p>
                  <p>This diſſolution or diſordering of the parts falls out ordinarily by the mixture of ſome Heterogeneous body; whoſe parts enter into the pores of its Surface ſtop them, and conſequently render them ſmaller. So that the <hi>Aetherial matter</hi> not being able to get out at this place, as freely as it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, forces the Obſtacle, diſorders the parts of this Body, and makes its paſſage, till it can continue its way through all with an equal facility.</p>
                  <p>When this motion which diſorders the parts of a Body is ſenſible, it is called <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation,</hi> and the Body by whoſe mixture it falls out, is called the <hi>Ferment.</hi> They diſtinguiſh five kinds of <hi>Fermentation.</hi> The firſt is called <hi>Bubbling.</hi> It is when the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Bodies excites ſometimes a viſible
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51501:14"/> motion of the parts, accompanied with ſmall Bubbles, and ſometimes ſmall Bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Air only. Theſe Bubbles are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd by the detachment of ſome moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate parts, which mingle with ſome parts of the Air, which is always to be met with amongſt the parts of Liquors. For in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating, they ſcatter the other parts thro' which they paſs, and make to be gathered together in theſe places, enough of Air to make up a little Bubble, which by its Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs aſcends to the Surface of the Liquor.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is <hi>Elevation,</hi> which is when by the mixture of certain Bodies, the Bodies are blown up and ſwelled, or to ſpeak better ratified. Which is done when the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution is not indeed ſenſible, but when the parts of the Diſſolvant are ſo figured that they cannot aſſociate with others with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking up together more place, than when they were ſeparated.</p>
                  <p>The third is <hi>Sparkling,</hi> which is when the mingled Bodies diſſolve with a kind of hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, accompanied with ſmall and interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſounds. Then the parts which are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51501:15"/> encline and bow by the action of the Ferment. Theſe parts thus bended, make a ſpring and excite thereby in the Air all thoſe little motions, which may produce in us the Senſation of Sound.</p>
                  <p>The fourth is <hi>Efferveſcence,</hi> which is done, to ſpeak properly, when by the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of bodies there is made a diſſolution of parts, accompanied with ſome degree of heat. For if the diſſolution be not made but by a great effort of the <hi>Aetherial mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> the motion which the parts acquire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes great enough to excite in us the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of heat.</p>
                  <p>In fine, the fifth is <hi>Exhalation,</hi> which is done when the diſordering of the parts is accompanied with Fumes. Which falls out when by the diſorder, ſome ſubtile parts acquire motion enough to aſcend viſibly in the Air, whiles the more groſs parts remain in the Maſſe.</p>
                  <p>After all theſe Reflections, it may eaſily appear that a <hi>Fermentation</hi> muſt follow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mixture of <hi>Acids</hi> with <hi>Alcalis.</hi> For <hi>Acids</hi> being pointed and <hi>Alcalis</hi> porous, if
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51501:15"/> they be mingled together, the points of the <hi>Acide</hi> will enter into the Pores of the <hi>Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> and render them conſequently ſmaller. So that the <hi>Aetherial matter</hi> cannot get out at that place with the ſame facility that it enters. It will therefore diſorder the parts amongſt which the points of the <hi>Acids</hi> have been received, and this diſorder or fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation will laſt till the <hi>Aetherial matter</hi> can paſs through all with an equal facility.</p>
                  <p>Moreover according as the Pores of the <hi>Alcalis</hi> are great or ſmall, and the points of the <hi>Acids</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>Alcalis</hi> great or ſmall, the Fermentation will be a <hi>Bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi> or an <hi>Elevation,</hi> or a <hi>Hiſſing,</hi> an <hi>Effer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſcence</hi> or <hi>Exhalation.</hi> Sometimes two of theſe kinds of <hi>Fermentations</hi> will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved at once, as the <hi>Hiſſing</hi> and <hi>Bubbling,</hi> the <hi>Exhalation</hi> and <hi>Efferveſcence,</hi> &amp;c. Sometimes three of them, whiles four, and ſometimes all of them. For according as the pores of the <hi>Alcalis</hi> are a little more or leſs ſtopt by the Angles of the <hi>Acids,</hi> the <hi>Aetherial matter</hi> will move with more or leſs force the parts of the Body which is Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51501:16"/> And it is from this greater or leſſer Agitation and Commotion that all the kinds of Fermentation derive their Origine.</p>
                  <p>From all this may be eaſily gathered that the <hi>Fermentation</hi> muſt laſt, when it is once begun, till the <hi>Aetherial matter</hi> can paſs without hinderance through the Pores of the <hi>Alcalis,</hi> which are mingled with the <hi>Acids.</hi> Which is done when the parts have been ſo diſordered, as that all the pores which were before formed, are deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and others formed of a near equal wideneſs. For when things are brought to this State, the ſubtile matter meets no ſtop in its paſſage. Therefore it paſſes ſtraight forward without moving any part of the Body through whoſe Pores it paſſes.</p>
                  <p>When the parts of this <hi>Alcalis</hi> have been diſordered thus by <hi>Acids,</hi> they recover ther firſt calm, and are ſo united with them, that there reſults from both a body of a third ſpecies, which is neither Acid nor Alcali, but a compoſure of both, which we ſhall call a <hi>Salt.</hi> So that <hi>Salts</hi> are nothing but porous Bodies, whoſe Surface is made
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51501:16"/> all rough by the points of the <hi>Acids</hi> which are faſtned to it.</p>
                  <p>There is no property remarked in <hi>Salt,</hi> which is not a Conſequent of what we have ſaid, as we could demonſtrate, if we did treat here of Salt as it ought to be treated in Phyſick. But ſince we ſpeak of it only as a reſult of the mixture of <hi>Alcalies</hi> with <hi>Acids,</hi> we ſhall ſay only, that as there is an almoſt infinite diverſity of <hi>Alcalies</hi> and <hi>Acids,</hi> ſo there are ſo many differences to be found amongſt <hi>Salts</hi> that it is impoſſible to determine them all. Nevertheleſs it is fit to remark that the moſt part of theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences depends upon <hi>Acids.</hi> For ſince <hi>Salts</hi> do not act on Bodies, but by the points of <hi>Acids,</hi> which are raiſed on the Surface of the <hi>Alcalies;</hi> all the difference which is to be met with in theſe properties, depends upon the Acid points, which act ſometimes one way, ſometimes another, as they are more or leſs ſharp, in a greater or leſſer number.</p>
                  <p>There are notwithſtanding <hi>Salts</hi> which differ amongſt themſelves by their <hi>Alcalies,</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51501:17"/> as may eaſily appear by what we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſaid. For if a certain <hi>Acid</hi> be mingled with a <hi>Volatile Alcalie,</hi> it is not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but there reſults from this mixture a Salt, which will be different from the Salt reſulting from the mixture of the ſame Acid with a <hi>Fixt Alcalie.</hi> For that the <hi>Volatile Alcalies</hi> have their parts incomparably more delicate than the <hi>Fixt Alcalies.</hi> From whence it follows, that the parts of the Salts muſt be alſo incomparably ſmaller, which ſuffices to make a difference between the Salts.</p>
                  <p>We may found a diviſion of Salts into <hi>fixt</hi> and <hi>Volatile,</hi> from what we have ſaid: The <hi>fixt Salts,</hi> are thoſe who have their parts ſo groſs, that they do not exhale with any heat, as <hi>Sea Salt, Vitriol, Salt petre,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Volatile Salts</hi> are thoſe which do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale by a moderate heat, as the <hi>Flowers of Sal Armoniack.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51501:17"/>
                  <head>SECT. V. <hi>Of Sulphurs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WE have ſaid nothing hitherto of the Figure, Structure and Magnitude of <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Alcalies,</hi> which may not alſo be underſtood of the Figure, Structure and Magnitude of <hi>Sulphurs.</hi> In effect, if it be conſidered attentively, it will eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that there is an infinite diverſity of <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs,</hi> by reaſon of their Figure. For if one <hi>Sulphur</hi> have parts more branched than another. if it have parts whoſe branches are ſhorter or longer, or otherwiſe ranged than another, it will be infallibly different, and conſequently capable of producing different effects. And foraſmuch as there may be amongſt all this an Infinity of Modifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it ſeems to me evident enough, that there may be alſo an Infinity of differences amonſt <hi>Sulphurs</hi> in reſpect of their Figure.</p>
                  <p>There is no leſs diverſity amongſt them in reſpect of their Structure. For ſince <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs</hi> are made by the aſſemblage of parts
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51501:18"/> of the <hi>Aetherial matter,</hi> ſince theſe parts may be aſſembled an infinite number of wayes, it is clear there may be of <hi>Sulphurs</hi> an infinite variety as to their Structure.</p>
                  <p>If moreover we conſider their Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, we perceive there is no leſs difference amongſt them as to this. For ſince matter is diviſible <hi>in infinitum,</hi> there may be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite difference amongſt the parts, ſome of which are groſſer than others, becauſe there is no Magnitude which may not be aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, without acquiring in the mean time the Magnitude of another which is a little groſſer than it.</p>
                  <p>We cannot therefore, what tour ſoever we take, place <hi>Sulphurs</hi> under certain kinds, by conſidering ſimply their Figure, Structure or Grandeur. Nevertheleſs, ſince we have reduc'd <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Alcalies</hi> under two kinds, by dividing them into <hi>Fixt</hi> and <hi>Volatile;</hi> notwithſtanding the infinite difference there is amongſt their parts, we may do here the ſame thing as to the <hi>Sulphurs.</hi> And ſince there are <hi>Sulphurs</hi> which do not exhale but very difficultly, and others
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51501:18"/> which exhale by moderate heat; we may be allowed to call the former <hi>Fixt Sulphurs,</hi> and the later <hi>Volatile Sulphurs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Fixt Sulphurs</hi> do not exhale but very hardly, for that their parts are groſs, and garniſh'd with groſs branches. For then as ſoon as they are agitated, they commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate almoſt all their motion, to the parts of the Bodies which environ them. So that they cannot acquire as much as were need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to exhale them without an extreme heat. Whereas the <hi>Volatile Sulphurs</hi> having their parts very delicate, and their Branches moſt ſubtile and cloſe, they move eaſily. Therefore a moderate heat is capable to give them agitation enough to raiſe them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Exhalation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> Of the mixture of <hi>Sulphurs</hi> with <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Alcalis.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AFter having examined the nature of <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> it will not be amiſs to mingle them with the Elements, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we know, to ſee what will follow.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51501:19"/>
                  <p>Since <hi>Acids</hi> are <hi>Molecules,</hi> which have many <hi>ſharp Angles</hi> on their ſurface, and <hi>Sulphurs</hi> are <hi>Molecules</hi> branched, if we min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle an <hi>Acid</hi> with a <hi>Sulphur,</hi> the <hi>Acid</hi> muſt coagulate the <hi>Sulphur:</hi> In effect, when we mingle an <hi>Acid</hi> with a <hi>Sulphur,</hi> the <hi>Acid</hi> engages its points amongſt the Branches of the <hi>Sulphur;</hi> by this means it holds the parts and gathers them ſo together, that by little and little they loſe their motion and co-agu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. So it may well he ſaid in general, that <hi>Acids co-agulate Sulphurs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the nature of <hi>Alcalies</hi> be well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it will eaſily appear that they muſt act on <hi>Sulphurs</hi> in a way quite oppoſite to that of the <hi>Acids.</hi> For if <hi>Acids</hi> co-agulate <hi>Sulphurs</hi> in embarraſſing their points in their Branches, the <hi>Alcalies</hi> which are without points muſt diſſolve them. In effect, when the <hi>Alcalies</hi> mingle with the <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> they ſeparate the parts, by placing themſelves amongſt them. They free them of one another, ſo that having no more union, the whole becomes more Liquid. And ſo it may well be ſaid in general, that <hi>Alcalies diſſolve Sulphurs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51501:19"/>
                  <head>SECT. VII. <hi>Of Phlegme.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BEſides <hi>Acids, Alcalies</hi> and <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> there are alſo <hi>oblong Molecules and Poliſht,</hi> whoſe two ends are almoſt blunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, like the extremities of an Egg. Theſe parts compoſe the <hi>Phlegme</hi> or Water, when they are aſſembled in a conſiderable quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity.</p>
                  <p>The difference which may be amongſt the Phlegme, as to their Figure, is ſo ſmall, that it does not merit we ſhould ſtop at it. For as they are all oblong and poliſht, the more or leſs that may be met with in this Figure, is not capable of producing effects, amongſt which there can be great difference</p>
                  <p>The ſame thing may be ſaid as to their Magnitude, which is never ſo different, as upon that head to diſtinguiſh them into <hi>Fixt and Volatile.</hi> On the contrary, for that their parts are poliſht and oblong, they do never embarraſſe ſo ſtrongly with other Principles, but that a little motion will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51501:20"/> them, and conſequently a very ſmall heat raiſe them into a Vapour So that to conſider them, after this manner all <hi>Phlegmes</hi> muſt be <hi>Volatile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>Of the mixture of</hi> Phlegme <hi>with</hi> Acids, Alcalies, <hi>and</hi> Sulphurs.</head>
                  <p>SInce <hi>Acids</hi> are the moſt ſolid and moſt angulous <hi>Molecules,</hi> all that can befall them by the mixture of <hi>Phelgme</hi> is diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In effect, when we conſider that parts ſo Figured as to have many angles on their ſurface, when they are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, do not touch frequently but by the points of their angles; it will eaſily appear, that having ſo ſlender an union, a little force will ſhake them. And foraſmuch as the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of a Body is nothing but the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of its parts, the <hi>Phlegme</hi> having enough of force to diſorder the parts, the <hi>Acids</hi> muſt be diſſolved.</p>
                  <p>Beſides the diſſolution of <hi>Acids,</hi> which is made by the mixture of <hi>Phlegme,</hi> their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51501:20"/> force is extremely weakned, which is not by the diviſion of their angles; but rather for that the <hi>Phlegme,</hi> which keep the parts of the <hi>Acids</hi> diſtant one from another, have not the ſame force to act upon certain Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, that we obſerve of <hi>Acids.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All that we have ſaid of the mixture of <hi>Phlegme</hi> with <hi>Acids,</hi> muſt alſo be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the mixture of <hi>Phlegme</hi> with <hi>Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</hi> For the ſame reaſon which has made us conclude that <hi>Phlegms</hi> diſſolve <hi>Acids,</hi> muſt make us think that they diſſolve <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies,</hi> Yet it is true that <hi>Phlegme</hi> muſt diſſolve <hi>Alcalies</hi> with ſome leſs trouble than they do Acids, for that the <hi>Alcalies</hi> being only porous parts, they touch them in more places than the <hi>Acids</hi> So that they require leſs force to diſorder them. Their diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt alſo diminiſh their activity, for the ſame reaſon that the diſſolution of <hi>Acids</hi> by a mixture of <hi>Phlegm,</hi> does weaken their force For if the parts of water cannot produce the ſame effect with the parts of <hi>Acids,</hi> neither can the ſame parts of water do the office of the <hi>Alcalies.</hi> The ſame
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51501:21"/> thing may be freely ſaid of <hi>Salts,</hi> for that the <hi>Saline Particles</hi> not being joyned together, but by the points of their <hi>Acids,</hi> they may be diſordered by the leaſt force, ſo that the <hi>Phlegme</hi> ſtriking againſt them, ſhake and ſeparate them one from another with great eaſe. The <hi>Phlegme</hi> muſt alſo weaken the Salts after the ſame manner that they dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the force of the <hi>Acids and the Alcalies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the Phlegmes muſt produce on the <hi>Sulphurs</hi> an effect quite contrary to what they produce on the <hi>Acids,</hi> the <hi>Alcalies</hi> and the <hi>Salts.</hi> For that the <hi>Sulphurs</hi> having their parts branched their brances do ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage amongſt one another, that they do not leave between them <hi>Interſtices</hi> or <hi>Spaces</hi> large enough to give way to the parts of the <hi>Phlegme.</hi> So that the <hi>Phlegms</hi> not being able to thruſt themſelves in amongſt the parts of the <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> and moreover not being able to ſeparate the parts which cloſe one upon another, without detaching them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when they are encountered, inſtead of diſſolving them, they muſt ſet them cloſer together. For the parts of the <hi>Phlegme</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51501:21"/> ſtricking on all ſides the parts of the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs,</hi> without ſeparating them from one another; and not being able to enter into the pores which they leave between them, they preſs them, the one againſt the other, and in ſome manner encreaſe their union. Hence it comes that Oyles cannot mingle with water.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IX. <hi>Of</hi> Earth.</head>
                  <p>WE have not only remarked <hi>Acids, Alcalies, Sulphur, Phlegme</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Molecules,</hi> but we have found alſo a fifth kind of Particles, which is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the reſt. Theſe are they which have not ſharp angles on their ſurface, but are rough and unequal, which have fewer pores than the <hi>Alcalies,</hi> and are leſs ſolid than the <hi>Acids,</hi> which have not the branches of the <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> nor the figure of the <hi>Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,</hi> in a word, which have nothing for their whole ſhare, but a ſurface very unequal, with a conſiderable enough ſolidity, and we have called them <hi>Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51501:22"/>
                  <p>When we conſider their Figure, Structure, and Magnitude, we can ſay nothing of them but what we have ſaid already of the Figure, Structure and Magnitude of <hi>Acids, Alcalies,</hi> and <hi>Sulphurs.</hi> Which has obliged us to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them into <hi>Fixt and Volatile.</hi> So we find that there may be parts of <hi>Earth</hi> groſs enough to ſubſiſt in the Fire, which we ſhall call <hi>Fixt Earth;</hi> and there may be alſo, which cannot ſubſiſt in the Fire, but do exhale by a moderate heat, and we ſhall name them <hi>Volatile Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. X.</hi> Of the mixture of the Earth with the other <hi>Elements.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF we reflect on the nature of <hi>Acids, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies, Sulphurs, Phlegme</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> we ſhall ſee that there cannot reſult a great matter from the mixture of <hi>Earth</hi> with the reſt. For it cannot diſſolve them, nor Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulate them, nor excite in them any Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation. So that all that it operates, is to trouble the purity of other Elements with which it is, and conſequently to diminiſh
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51501:22"/> their force. Nevertheleſs, as the moſt part of Bodies are compoſed of many of our Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſometimes of them all, the Earth is not entirely uſeleſs. Since it finds a place amongſt the other Elements, and fills the ſpaces which they leave between them, and by this means renders the whole body more maſſy and more firm.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. XI.</hi> Of the manner of knowing the <hi>Elements</hi> which enter into the Compoſition of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Bodies.</head>
                  <p>IT is nothing to know that there are <hi>Acids, Alcalies, Sulphurs,</hi> &amp;c. We muſt know which of them are in particular Bodies To come to the knowledge of this, we make uſe of <hi>Chymie,</hi> becauſe it ſeparates the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments one from another, and collects them as much as is poſſible in their Elementary purity.</p>
                  <p>It accompliſheth this by the means of Fire, which is an univerſal Diſſolvant The Fire by its great ſubtilty enters into the pores
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51501:23"/> of Bodies, and by its great agitation moves their parts and breaks their union. So that in continuing to agitate and diſunite them, thoſe which are moſt <hi>Volatile</hi> ſeparate from the reſt, and the more Fixt abide in the Fire. After which we ſeparate them from one another, by the mixture of ſome other Body; and in fine, collect them in their Elementary purity.</p>
                  <p>For example, if I would know of what principles a <hi>Plant</hi> is compoſed, I take a great enough quantity of it, beat it in a Mortar, and without any more adoe, put it in a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curbite. I place my Cucurbite on a Furnace, and afterwards put on the Cucurbite an Alembick, and to the Pipe of this Alembick, I put a Recipient I give it Fire as it ought to have, which acting upon my Cucurbite, makes by Vapour to aſcend into the Alem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick, all that is <hi>Volatile</hi> in the Plant. Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily if it be an Odorous Plant, we find ſome drops of <hi>Sulphur</hi> which ſwim upon the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. We call theſe Sulphurs <hi>Eſſences.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe Sulphurs, which are known for ſuch, not only for that they eaſily kindle
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51501:23"/> when they are caſt into the Fire, but for that <hi>Acids</hi> co-agulate them, and <hi>Alcalies</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them. There are ſome <hi>Acids,</hi> or ſome <hi>Volatile Alcalies,</hi> which are diſſolved in the Water. We know them by means of the Fermentation which they excite, either with <hi>Acids,</hi> or with <hi>Alcalies.</hi> For if they ferment with <hi>Alcalies,</hi> we do not fail to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that they are <hi>Acids;</hi> and if they fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>Acids,</hi> we conclude they are <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies.</hi> Thus we diſcover that in the Plant there are <hi>Phlegme, Volatile Sulphurs, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile Acids</hi> or <hi>Alcalies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After this, that we may know what there is of Fixt; I take what remains in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of my Cucurbite, and expoſe it to the Fire; if it take flame, I conclude that in the Plant there are fixt <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> which could not aſcend by Diſtillation. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I reduce the whole to aſhes, and to know of what theſe aſhes are compoſed, I make a Lee of them. The Water diſſolves all that there is of <hi>Acid, Alcali</hi> and of <hi>Earth.</hi> I paſs my diſſolution through Gray-paper, to the end I may have nothing but the <hi>Salts,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51501:24"/> Acids,</hi> or <hi>Alcalies</hi> diſſolved in Water. And the <hi>Earth</hi> being too groſs to paſs through the pores of the Paper, remains within, and then I ſee how much <hi>Earth</hi> enters into the Compoſition of the Plant. I take after this my diſſolution which I ſet upon the Fire. The Fire by its activity makes all the water to exhale, and what there is of fixt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the bottom of the Veſſel. I exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it, and ſee if it be an <hi>Alcali,</hi> by ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it with an <hi>Acid;</hi> or if it be an <hi>Acid,</hi> by mingling it with an <hi>Alcali,</hi> by the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which it will excite with the one or with the other. But if it do not ferment at all, neither with <hi>Acids</hi> not with <hi>Alcalies,</hi> I conclude that it is fixt Salt.</p>
                  <p>Thus I know all the Elements which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Compoſition of a <hi>Plant,</hi> and how we may operate almoſt upon all Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial Bodies, to extract their Elements, Chymie is the only Science whereby we may know aright of what Bodies are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
                  <p>The moſt part do not grant this, becauſe they imagine that the Fire acting upon Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51501:24"/> changes all their parts; ſo that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Elements which we extract from Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies by the means of Chymie, were not there in their opinion, ſuch as they are when we extract them. But I have great reaſons to be of another Sentiment. Which are 1. for that the Fire does not change <hi>Acids</hi> into <hi>Alcalies,</hi> not <hi>Alcalies</hi> into <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs.</hi> For though the Fire by its great agitation may produce ſome change into the parts of a Body; yet it is inconceivable that it can change the Principles by ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them of their Nature to cloath them With the nature of another. Thus there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though it were even true, that the Fire ſhould produce ſome change in the parts of Bodies upon which we operate to extract their Elements; yet it is certain that what is extracted of <hi>Alcali,</hi> was there under the form of <hi>Alcali;</hi> what is extracted of <hi>Acid,</hi> was there under the form of <hi>Acid,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But that which obliges me chiefly to think that the Fire makes no change in the Elements of Bodies which are extracted by Chymie, is, that if we take the Spirit of <hi>Salt</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:51501:25"/> and mingle it with the Fixt <hi>Alcali</hi> of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> we make a true Salt of it, and if we take the Spirit of <hi>Nitre,</hi> and mix it with the Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> we make a true <hi>Nitre</hi> of it. Nevertheleſs all they who can ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in Chymie, know well enough that the Fire muſt be blown with an extreme vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to diſtil the Spirit of <hi>Salt</hi> and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Nitre.</hi> So if the Fire ſhould produce any change in the Elements that are drawn from Bodies by its means, it would be chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Diſtillation of the Spirit of <hi>Salt</hi> and Spirit of <hi>Nitre,</hi> where it muſt act with all its force.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs, Experience makes appear that there is no change produced, and that the Spirit of <hi>Salt</hi> and Spirit of <hi>Nitre</hi> were ſuch in the <hi>Salt</hi> and in the <hi>Nitre,</hi> as they are when the Fire has ſeparated them from the other Element, with which they muſt be mingled to conſtitute the <hi>Salt</hi> and the <hi>Nitre;</hi> ſince we make a true <hi>Salt</hi> and a true <hi>Nitre,</hi> by mingling them with that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Element, which is the <hi>Salt</hi> of <hi>Tartar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We are convinced by true Philoſophy,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51501:25"/> that Odours are nothing but the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til parts which get away from Odorous Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and ſpread in the Air by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halation. We are not ignorant likewiſe that it is from the different Magnitude and Figure of the parts, that all the diverſity of Odours does proceed. So that there muſt be a certain Magnitude and Figure in theſe parts to excite a particular Odour. And if it fall out that this Magnitude or Figure comes to be changed by whatſoever cauſe, the Odour which theſe parts ſhould excite after this in us would not be the ſame. But we extract by Chymie the Odorous parts of Odoriferous Bodies, without making any change in them: Since they excite in us the ſame Odours which the Bodies do from whence they were extracted: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Eſſence of <hi>Roſemary, Gilly-flowers, Cinamon,</hi> &amp;c. from whence we may with reaſon conclude, that the Fire does not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any changes in the Elements which are extracted from Bodies by the means of Chymie.</p>
                  <p>And ſince many different Liquors are to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51501:26"/> be found in Animals, which are compoſed of divers Elements, we ſhall make uſe of the Chymie to ſeparate them from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to examine them apart, that we may know the nature of each in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular After this we ſhall eaſily ſee what may be their uſes in the animal Oeconomy, and what effects do depend upon them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="discourse">
               <head>The ſecond Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Blood.</head>
               <p>WHen I ſtrike a Lance into any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward part of a living Animal, I remark that there comes from the wound I have made a red Liquor, which I call Blood.</p>
               <p>I imagine that it is very important to know the nature of it aright, for I find it ſo ſpread through all the Body, that there is no part which is not watered with it. Which obliges me to gather a little of it in a Veſſel and to know if it be not ſome of our Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or if it be not a compoſition of them. I mingle it firſt with <hi>Acids;</hi> and I find that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51501:26"/> they co-agulate it; in ſuch a manner not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that they co-agulate but a part of it, and that remains another very Liquid and Tranſparent, which we call <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity.</hi> In the ſecond place I take the Sero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and mingle it with <hi>Acids,</hi> and I find that there is made by this mixture a little Fermentation.</p>
               <p>From hence I conclude, that there are in the Blood much <hi>Sulphur,</hi> and ſome <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cali;</hi> that the <hi>Sulphurs</hi> are that which has been co-agulated by the <hi>Acids;</hi> and that the <hi>Alcalies</hi> are that which ferments with the <hi>Acids,</hi> which we mingled with the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not ſatisfy my ſelf with this, I take <hi>Alcalies</hi> and mingle them with the Blood, to confirm what I conjecture by ſome new Experiment. And it falls out that the Blood is extremely diſſolved by this mixture. And as I know that the effect of <hi>Alcalies</hi> on <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs</hi> is Diſſolution, I am confirmed the more in the opinion I have, that in the Blood there is a great deal of <hi>Sulphur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſmall Fermentation which the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51501:27"/> 
                  <hi>Acids</hi> have excited in the Seroſity, makes me think that there is in the Seroſity ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than <hi>Alcalies;</hi> and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent that there is through all the Blood ſome other Principle than <hi>Sulphurs</hi> and <hi>Alcalies.</hi> To know therefore the truth of the matter, I take a conſiderable quantity of Blood, I put it in a Cucurbite, I place my Cucurbite in a Furnace to diſtil ſome part of it by Sand. I adapt a Head to my Cucurbite, and to the Pipe of the Head I apply a Recipient. I take care to lute the Junctures well, and give it a little Fire at firſt, and augmenting it afterwards by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, I dry gently all the Blood which I had put in my Cucurbite</p>
               <p>Whilſt the Blood is thus drying, there ariſe ſome Vapours in the Alembic, which gathering in its concave Surface, run in drops of Water through the Pipe into the Recipient. I take this water and try it, by putting it on my Tongue. A little favour that it excites there, makes me judge that it is not pure <hi>Phlegme;</hi> I mingle <hi>Alcalies</hi> with it, and I remark no Fermentation.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51501:27"/> Which makes me think, that what is in this Water is not <hi>Acid.</hi> I mingle after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Acids</hi> with it, and I perceive by the light Fermentation that ariſes from this mixture, that there are <hi>Alcaline</hi> parts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely <hi>Volatile</hi> mingled with much <hi>Phlegme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I take out (after this) that which is dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my Cucurbite, and I put it in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort, which I place on a Furnace proper for this. I give it Fire by degrees, and there comes out of my Retort a ſtinking Oyl, which is the <hi>Sulphureous</hi> part of the Blood. With the ſtinking Oyl there comes out a great quantity of whitiſh Particles, which ſtick to the neck of the Cornute, and to the concave Surface of the Recipient, as if it were a moſt delicate hoar Froſt.</p>
               <p>I examine the ſtinking Oyl, by the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Alcalies.</hi> The <hi>Acids</hi> Co-agulate it, the <hi>Alcalies</hi> Liquify it, which will not let me doubt that it is a true <hi>Sulphur.</hi> I do the ſame with the whitiſh Particles, which I rub off from the neck of the Cornute, and the ſides of the Reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pient,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51501:28"/> and I learn by the great Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they make with <hi>Acids,</hi> that it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an <hi>Alcalie,</hi> which riſing by a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate heat, is very <hi>Volatile.</hi> I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore three <hi>Volatile</hi> Principles which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Blood, <hi>viz.</hi> A moſt conſiderable quantity of <hi>Phlegme,</hi> much of a <hi>Volatile Sulphur,</hi> and yet more of a <hi>Volatile Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</hi> That I may know now what remains in the the bottom of the Cornute, I put it in a Crucible, and Calcine it by a wheel Fire. There is ſome ſmall matter that yet Exhales. And in fine, after the whole have been well Calcin'd, I make a <hi>Lixivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> of it, which I filter. I make a part of the Water to evaporate, which makes up the <hi>Lixivium.</hi> I put the reſt in a cool place, and there Chryſtallizes ſomewhat about my Veſſel in form of a <hi>Salt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I take this <hi>Salt</hi> and mingle it with <hi>Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> and <hi>Acids.</hi> The <hi>Alcalies</hi> do not move it, but the <hi>Acids</hi> excite a Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet leſs than what they do with the <hi>Volatile Alcali</hi> of Blood. Which makes me think that it is a <hi>Fixt Alcalie</hi> with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51501:28"/> which there may be ſome <hi>Acid</hi> mingled.</p>
               <p>I perceive after this, that there remains ſome Terreſtreity in the Paper through which I filtered the <hi>Lixivium,</hi> from whence I had extracted the <hi>Fixt Alcalie.</hi> So that after having examin'd all, I find that the Blood is a Compoſure of <hi>Volatile Alcalie, Fixt Alcalie, Volatile Sulphur, Phlegme, Earth,</hi> and it may be ſome little <hi>Acid</hi> mingled with the <hi>Fixt Alcalie.</hi> So that it abounds more in <hi>Sulphur,</hi> in <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile Alcalie.</hi> and in <hi>Phlegme,</hi> than in any other Principle. For there is little of <hi>Fixt Salt,</hi> and almoſt no Terreſtreity.</p>
               <p>We may eaſily underſtand by this, the reaſon why through a Microſcop there are to be ſeen in the Blood many ſmall red Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bules which ſwim in a Chryſtalline Liquor, while the Blood is put into ſmall Pipes of Glaſs. The <hi>Sulphurs</hi> which are more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to keep themſelves united to one another, becauſe their branches are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barraſſed, do ſwim in a Liquor compos'd of <hi>Phlegmes</hi> and <hi>Alcalies.</hi> The <hi>Phlegmes</hi> by their motion preſs thoſe branched Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51501:29"/> one againſt another, and oblige them to form ſmall <hi>Sulphureous</hi> Globules, after the ſame manner that the Air makes the drops of water Sphaerical. And the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies</hi> make the ſmalneſs of theſe Globu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and oblige the Sulphureous parts of the Blood to aſſemble in ſmall Bodies, by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them ſeparated one from another.</p>
               <p>We ſee alſo the reaſon wherefore curd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Blood, after having been waſhed in cold water, ſeems all Fibrous: For cold water diſſolves the <hi>Alcalies</hi> and carries them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Afterwards it aſſembles the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs,</hi> which fall down to the bottom of the Veſſel like a Glairous matter, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of ſmall Fibres like Glue.</p>
               <p>It is alſo for the ſame reaſon, that when we receive the Blood amongſt hot water, as ſoon as is comes out of the Vein, there gathers about ſmall Rods which you put into it a Mucilaginous and Glairous ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For the <hi>Alcalies</hi> ſpread through all the water with the <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> and ſtrike together againſt the Surface of the ſmall Rods. The <hi>Alcalies</hi> never fix to them,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51501:29"/> becauſe they have not proper Particles for this; but the <hi>Sulphurs</hi> inſinuate into the Pores of the Wood, which are opened by the heat of Water, the extremities of their Branches. So that finding themſelves en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, they continue fixed there, and the other <hi>Sulphureous</hi> parts of the Blood which ſwim in the Water joyn to the firſt, ſo that <hi>in fine,</hi> when the Water is become Cold, we find the <hi>Sulphurs</hi> of the Blood upon the Surface of the Rods, like to a Glaire, or a Mucilage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="discourse">
               <head>The third Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Glandules.</head>
               <p>WHen we follow the <hi>Arteries</hi> and the Veins, wee find that a great number of their Branches end at certain round Bodies involved in a moſt delicate Coat; and from which Bodies there comes a Canal, and from thence flows a Liquor quite different from the Blood.</p>
               <p>The Anatomiſts call theſe round Bodies,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51501:30"/> 
                  <hi>Glandules.</hi> There are three conſiderable things to be remarked in them. The firſt, that each <hi>Glandule</hi> receives a Branch of an <hi>Artery,</hi> which carries the Blood to it, and that there goes from it a Branch of a Vein which carries the Blood away. The ſecond, that there goes a Canal from each <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule</hi> from whence flows a Liquor different from the Blood. And the thrid, that the Compoſition of <hi>Glandules</hi> is of two ſorts, ſome are nothing but a heap of ſmall Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels contorted, which reuniting, make the Canal through which there flows a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Liquor. And others, are nothing but an aſſemblage of little Veſicles. In ſome places theſe Veſicles are angular, and there is a Communication between their Cavities. So that they end all into two or three, whoſe prolongation makes the Canal, from whence flows the Liquor which is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the Blood. In ſome others there are ſeparated Veſicles, which ſend each one in Particular a little Canal. Thoſe, which are nothing but a heap of Contorted Veſſels we ſhall call <hi>Vaſcular Glandules,</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:51501:30"/> and thoſe which are compoſed of nothing but a heap of Veſicles, we ſhall name <hi>Veſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Glandules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we reaſon upon theſe three things, we will eaſily diſcover the nature of <hi>Glandules.</hi> The arteries bring the Blood, which after having watered the Veſſels or Veſicles of the <hi>Glandules,</hi> returns by the Veins which go from them, Now the <hi>Glandules</hi> are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Compoſure of ſmall Veſſels or Veſicles, full of a Liquor different from the Blood. But for that we have not hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diſcovered any Veſſel which brings any thing to the <hi>Glandules,</hi> but the Arteries which carries Blood thither, we may well think that this Liquor is a certain portion of Arterial Blood, which has been ſeparated from it by the Veſſels or Veſicles, and has been collected into their Cavity, from whence it comes that this Liquor flows alwayes from the <hi>Glandule</hi> by the little Canal which comes from it, and which we ſhall call the <hi>Excretory Canal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The difference that is between this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor and the Blood, ought not to keep us
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51501:31"/> from being of this ſentiment. For ſince the Blood is compoſed of heterogeneous Principles, a certain portion of one, or many of theſe Principles, may be ſeparated from the Blood into the Cavity of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels or Veſicles of the <hi>Glandules.</hi> And for that the principles of the Blood are not to be met with there, whether in number or proportion ſufficient to make Blood; the Liquor that reſults from this Aſſemblage, muſt be a Liquor quit different from Blood.</p>
               <p>Thus the Liquor that flows from the <hi>Glandules</hi> by their Excretory Veſſels, muſt come from the Blood. But that which confirms us yet more in this Sentiment, is that we can extract nothing from this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor by Chymie, which we do not draw from Blood: which is an evident enough mark, that this Liquor is no other thing, but an Aſſemblage of certain principles which have been ſeparated from the Blood, by means of the <hi>Glandule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Liquor which one <hi>Glandule</hi> ſeparats from the Blood, we obſerve that it is alwayes the ſame. Nevertheleſs, we
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51501:31"/> muſt not for this imagine that all <hi>Glandu es</hi> ſeparate the ſame Liquor Experience makes appear to us moſt conſiderable differences between the Liquors which proceed from different <hi>Glandules.</hi> Which abundantly ſhews, that for the moſt part, diverſe <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules</hi> ſeparate different principles from the maſſe of Blood.</p>
               <p>But as this does not entirely ſatisfie the mind, it will not perhaps be impertinent to enquire into the manner, how the <hi>Glandules</hi> do ſeparate from the Blood, the Liquors which flow from them. That wee may ſucceed in this enquiry, I remark that the <hi>Arteries</hi> bring the Blood into the Body of the <hi>Glandule,</hi> that the Blood is a Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of heterogeneous parts, that ſome of theſe heterogeneous parts go out of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the <hi>Arteries,</hi> and gather into the Cavity of the Veſſels or Veſicles, which compoſe the <hi>Glandule.</hi> From whence I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that there are paſſages from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the <hi>Arteries</hi> into the Cavity of the Veſſels or Veſicles of the <hi>Glandules,</hi> and ſuch Paſſages as that no other principle of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51501:32"/> the Blood can paſs thither, but theſe which are abſolutely neceſſary for making up the Liquor which flows from each <hi>Glandule</hi> in particular. We ſhall call theſe ſorts of Holes, or Paſſages, <hi>Pores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the end that the thing be thus done, theſe Pores muſt be proportioned to the Magnitude and Figure of the parts which are ſeparated from the Blood, that they may be gathered into the Veſſels or Veſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the <hi>Glandules,</hi> whiles parts of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Magnitude and Figure cannot paſs through them. For then the Blood com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to run in the <hi>Arteries,</hi> which are ſpread through the ſubſtance of the Veſſels or Veſicles of the <hi>Glandules,</hi> thoſe of its parts which can paſs through the Pores, when they come thither are engaged in them. And for that the Blood continues to move in the <hi>Arteries,</hi> the parts which are engaged in the Pores through which they can paſs, are thruſt forward, and being followed by others which have the ſame fate, they are in fine preſs'd foreward into the Cavity of the Veſſels or Veſicles of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51501:32"/> 
                  <hi>Glandules</hi> There they mingle with many others which are come thither after the ſame manner, and compoſe with them the Liquor which flows from the <hi>Glandule</hi> through its Excretory Veſſel.</p>
               <p>But for that the Liquor which runs from one <hi>Glandule</hi> is made up of Heterogeneous parts, it muſt needs be that the <hi>Pores</hi> of each <hi>Artery</hi> are not all equal. So that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Liquor of one <hi>Glandule</hi> is compoſed of <hi>Sulphurs, Alcalies</hi> or <hi>Phlegms,</hi> there muſt be proportionably in the <hi>Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of that <hi>Glandule, Pores</hi> fitted to let <hi>Alcalies, Sulphurs</hi> or <hi>Phlegms</hi> paſs through them.</p>
               <p>We may even affirm, that not only the <hi>Pores</hi> of the <hi>Arteries</hi> of <hi>Glandules</hi> are not all equal amongſt themſelves; but alſo that thoſe of the <hi>Arteries</hi> of one <hi>Glandule</hi> are ſometimes entirely different from thoſe of the <hi>Arteries</hi> of another. The reaſon is, that there comes ſometimes from one <hi>Glandule</hi> a Liquor entirely different from that which flows from another.</p>
               <p>After this, it is to be obſerved, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51501:33"/> there are <hi>Glandules</hi> to be met with alone, without being joyned to any other. Theſe are called <hi>Conglobated Glandules,</hi> becauſe they are conſidered as little <hi>Globes,</hi> which ſeparate a Liquor from the Blood. But when there is an aſſemblage of them, and that they are all folded up within one Coat, and that all their Excretory Veſſels are united in one, and ſo compoſe one Canal through which the Liquor runs, which they have all with one accord ſeparated from the Blood, they are called <hi>Conglome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. Glandules</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The greateſt part of the <hi>Conglomerated Glandules</hi> are <hi>Vaſcular,</hi> and the moſt part of the <hi>Conglobated</hi> are <hi>Veſicular.</hi> As thoſe may ſee who will give themſelves the trouble to make the enquiry. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there are <hi>Conglobated Glandules</hi> which are <hi>Vaſcular</hi> in ſome Animals, and <hi>Veſicular</hi> in others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="discourse">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:51501:33"/>
               <head>The Fourth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Nerves.</head>
               <p>THe Surface of the <hi>Brain</hi> and of the <hi>Cerebellum,</hi> as well as the inner part of the Marrow of the Back-bone, are made up of nothing but a heap of ſmall round Bodies. It is obſerved that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Arteries,</hi> they ſend off Veins, and there goes from them a ſmall white <hi>Fibre.</hi> The <hi>Arteries</hi> do bring them Blood, after that it has watered them it returns by the Veins. But ſince it is not found in the Veins with the ſame qualities which it had in the <hi>Arteries,</hi> we may well conjecture that it has left ſomething in theſe round Bodies, which occaſions all this Change.</p>
               <p>In effect, this Change does not befall the Blood, but either by the Addition of ſome new matter, or the loſs of ſome of its parts. It will eaſily appear that it is not from the addition of any new matter, if we conſider that theſe little round Bodies receive no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but from the <hi>Arteries.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:51501:34"/>
               <p>For if they made this alteration in the Blood by communicating unto it any new Liquor, they ſhould receive it elſewhere. The reaſon is, that the Blood paſſes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually through theſe round Bodies, and is alſo continually changed. So they muſt inceſſantly Communicate unto it this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, which cannot be, if they do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it from ſome inexhauſtible ſource. Since therefore this ſource is not known, we may reaſonably think that this Change does not befall the Blood by the addition of any new matter.</p>
               <p>It muſt needs then be occaſioned by the loſs of ſome of its parts. And becauſe this change is ſenſible, it cannot fall out but by the loſs of a conſiderable number of its parts; which ſince they cannot ſtay in theſe round Bodies, becauſe they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually parting from the Blood, they muſt needs go through ſome paſſage to be carried elſewhere.</p>
               <p>When we examine narrowly theſe round Bodies, we find nothing in each of them, but <hi>Arteries, Veins,</hi> and a ſmall white
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51501:34"/> 
                  <hi>Fibre.</hi> The parts which are ſeparated from the Blood, do not go by the <hi>Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſince it is by the <hi>Artery</hi> that the Blood comes to the round Body; neither do they go by the <hi>Vein;</hi> for if this were, there would be no difference between the Blood of the <hi>Artery</hi> and that of the <hi>Vein.</hi> It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains therefore, that they paſs through the ſmall white <hi>Fibre.</hi> And thus we find that the Surface of the Brain, is nothing but a compoſure of ſmall <hi>Glandules,</hi> which do receive Blood from the <hi>Arteries,</hi> which ſend it off by the <hi>Veins,</hi> and which have their Excretory Veſſels from whence the the Liquor flows which they have ſeparat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Blood.</p>
               <p>There are two ſorts of Subſtance taken notice of in the Brain, the <hi>Cerebellum</hi> and the <hi>Spinal Marrow.</hi> The firſt is that Glandulous Subſtance, which making the Surface of the Brain and <hi>Cerebellum,</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their <hi>Cortical Subſtance.</hi> In the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Marrow,</hi> it is found in the middle co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with the other Subſtance. And the other, which is a white Subſtance, more
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51501:35"/> firm than it, is nothing but the aſſemblage of the Excretory Veſſels of the Glandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Subſtance. They call it in the Brain and Cerebellum, the <hi>Callous Body,</hi> or the <hi>Marrowie Subſtance.</hi> And in the Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone it has no Name.</p>
               <p>The Veſſels which compoſe the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Body</hi> of the Brain and Cerebellum, are ſo interwoven, that they reſemble a Net. It has not as yet been diſcovered, whether they are Inoſculated, or if the Nets be made only by their paſſing one over another.</p>
               <p>In fine, they gather into little Bundles, which are found ſhut up into Membranous ſheaths. According as they advance into the Body of the Animal, they are divided into many ſmall branches, and after this manner ſpread themſelves through all. So that there are very few parts in the Body of an Animal, which does not receive its portion of them.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Nerves</hi> the Excretory Veſſels of which they are compoſed have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; even it is not remarked that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:51501:35"/> they are Interwoven. But they extend themſelves in length, coucht one above another, as if they were ſmall Bundles of little Cords.</p>
               <p>I ſay, this falls out in the <hi>Nerves,</hi> that it may be obſerved that it is quite otherwiſe in certain Tumours faſtned to the <hi>Nerves,</hi> which are called <hi>Olive</hi> Bodies, or <hi>Ganglions.</hi> For theſe Olive Bodies are not formed but by the interweaving of the Nervous Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels. Even as the threed of which a ſling is made, ſeems to take up more room in the Body of the ſling where the Stone is plac'd, than in the ſtrings which are on either ſide.</p>
               <p>Many <hi>Nerves</hi> meet together in diverſe places of the Body of an Animal, and are ſo interlaced one with another, that the Anatomiſts call theſe aſſemblages <hi>Plexus.</hi> They part afterwards from theſe <hi>Plexus,</hi> and ſpread round about.</p>
               <p>It muſt carefully be obſerved, that when many <hi>Nerves</hi> meet in one, there is not an Anaſtomoſis of the Veſſels that Compoſe them, but only of their Coats. And when a <hi>Nerve</hi> is divided into many branches, its
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51501:36"/> particular Veſſels are not branched into many, but the diviſion is only in their cover, and the Veſſels which are in one Bundle, are parted into many Bundles.</p>
               <p>In fine, the uſe of the <hi>Nerves</hi> is to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute the Liquor which runs into the <hi>Fibres,</hi> into all the parts where they ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate. As to this Liquor, it muſt needs be compoſed of the moſt ſubtile and moſt <hi>Volatile</hi> parts of the Blood. It is look'd upon as a very ſubtile wind which paſſes through the <hi>Fibres</hi> of the <hi>Nerves,</hi> and that not without reaſon. For ſince it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcapes our eyes, and that the beſt Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopes are not capable to make us ſee it; we may well think that it is the moſt ſubtile of all the Liquors which are ſeparated from the Blood through the <hi>Glandules</hi> of the Body of an Animal This Liquor is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Animal Spirits,</hi> becauſe of its great ſubtility, and becauſe it is the Soul, which makes Animals to live.</p>
               <p>Though nothing of this Liquor can be gathered to examine its nature, by ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it with <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Alcalies,</hi> yet we are
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:51501:36"/> enclined to think that the <hi>Volatile Alcalie</hi> prevails in it with an extremely <hi>Volatile Sulphur.</hi> The reaſon is, that all <hi>Volatile Alcali's</hi> taken inwardly, do encreaſe the Animal Spirits, the <hi>Volatile Sulphurs</hi> do almoſt the ſame thing, and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which does ſo much encreaſe their quantity, as <hi>Sulphureous Volatile Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> as all <hi>Volatile Alcalies</hi> Aromatiz'd are.</p>
               <p>The effect of <hi>Alcalies</hi> upon <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> confirms us in this Sentiment For <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies</hi> do diſſolve <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> by ſeparating their parts one from another, and by this means hinder their branches from grapling together. For this cauſe the Interſtices or Intervals of the branches are repleniſht with <hi>Aetherial matter,</hi> as well as the Pores which remain between the <hi>Sulphurs</hi> and the <hi>Alcalies;</hi> which being larger than if the Liquor were ſimply <hi>Alcaline</hi> or <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureous,</hi> do alſo contain within them much more of <hi>Aetherial matter.</hi> And for as much as this <hi>Aetherial matter</hi> is highly agitated, it moves with much
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:51501:37"/> force all the parts of this Liquor, which contributes not a little to its activity and its ſubtility.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="discourse">
               <head>The fifth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Muſcles.</head>
               <p>WHen we follow the <hi>Nerves</hi> and <hi>Arteries,</hi> we find that the moſt part of their branches do loſe themſelves into <hi>Carneous Bodies,</hi> which are covered over with a moſt delicate Membrane, and are called <hi>Muſcles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three ſorts of parts do enter into their Compoſition. 1. We diſcover in them a great many <hi>Arteries</hi> and <hi>Veins.</hi> 2 <hi>Nerves,</hi> and in fine, ſmall <hi>Fibres,</hi> which are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Arteries, Veins</hi> nor <hi>Nerves,</hi> but which are certain ſmall long <hi>Filaments,</hi> moſt delicate, and yet very ſtrong.</p>
               <p>The manner after which they are rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Muſcles,</hi> has ſomething in it very
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51501:37"/> remarkable. At firſt we find them all ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, and then they reſemble a ſtring. Afterwards they ſeparate from one another, and receive amongſt them diverſe branches of <hi>Arteries</hi> &amp; <hi>Veins.</hi> In fine they unite together, and make again a Cord The firſt and the ſecond Cords are called <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, or the Head and Tail of the Muſcle.</hi> And that part which is plac'd between the Head and the Tail, and which is the place where the <hi>Fibres</hi> of the <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> ſeparate from one another, and where they receive the Veins and Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries amongſt them, is called the <hi>Belly of the Muſcle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Fibres</hi> are all parallel, both in the <hi>Tendons</hi> and in the <hi>Belly.</hi> In the <hi>Tendons</hi> ſome of them are longer than others, and in the <hi>Belly</hi> all are of the ſame length. By the order they are plac'd in, they make an <hi>Obliquangular Parallelogram</hi> in the <hi>Belly</hi> of the <hi>Muſcle.</hi> And they are ſo cloſely preſt together in the <hi>Tendons,</hi> that they reſemble two Strings, which draw the <hi>Obliquangular Parallelogram</hi> by its op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51501:38"/> ſides, as may be ſeen in this Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>A. B. repreſents a <hi>Tendon,</hi> or the head of a <hi>Muſcle,</hi> B. C. the <hi>Belly,</hi> and C. D. the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tendon,</hi> or the <hi>Tail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Arteries</hi> and <hi>Veins</hi> which are ſpread through the muſcle, are not to be found but in its Belly; if they be found ſometimes in the <hi>Tendons,</hi> they are ſo few, that they are not to be regarded. So the <hi>Tendons</hi> are nothing but the Aſſemblage of the ſimple Fibres, which for this wee ſhall call the <hi>Tendinous Fibres.</hi> whereas the Interſtices, which are amongſt them in the Belly of the muſcle, are all repleniſht with <hi>Veins</hi> and <hi>Arteries.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:51501:38"/>
               <p>From hence comes the difference, which we obſerve between the colour of the <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> and that of the Belly of the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. The <hi>Tendons</hi> are Brown and the Belly is Red. And it is this part of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals compoſed of <hi>Tendinous Fibres</hi> and of <hi>Veins</hi> and <hi>Arteries,</hi> which wee call <hi>Fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore we muſt not imagine that <hi>Fleſh</hi> is Red of its ſelf, no more than we are to beleive that a Glaſs full of red Wine is red of its ſelf. But rather as the Glaſs appears Red, becauſe the Liquor that is within it is of that colour, even ſo <hi>Fleſh</hi> and all the other parts of the Body of an Animal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Red, only becauſe of the Redneſs of the Blood which is contain'd in the <hi>Veins</hi> and <hi>Arteries</hi> of theſe ſorts of parts.</p>
               <p>This truth is demonſtrated by an Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which renders it Inconteſtable. That is, if you make Injections of warm water into the <hi>Arteries,</hi> which ſpread their Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches through the Fleſh, after you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated frequently the Injection, the <hi>Fleſh</hi> becomes of the colour of the <hi>Tendons</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:51501:39"/>
               <p>The <hi>Muſcles</hi> are not only compoſed of <hi>Arteries, Veins</hi> and <hi>Tendinous Fibres,</hi> but the <hi>Nerves</hi> alſo make one of their parts. They march firſt upon their Coat and pierce it. When they have pierced it, they divide themſelves in moſt delicate Branches, which are moſculated with the <hi>Tendinous Fibres.</hi> Sometimes the <hi>Nerves</hi> enter into the <hi>Tendons,</hi> and ſometimes into the <hi>Belly</hi> of the <hi>Muſcles.</hi> But in what part ſoever they enter we find alwayes the extremites of their Branches to end at the <hi>Tendinous Fibres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe <hi>Tendinons Fibres</hi> have a Cavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that goes through them, like unto a Tube or Pipe. Indeed this Cavity cannnot be ſeen by the eye, but there is an Experiment which abundantly ſhews the neceſſity of it, that it cannot be Contradicted by thoſe who will hearken to reaſon. The Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is that alwayes when a <hi>Muſcle</hi> acts, its <hi>Fibres</hi> are conſiderably ſhortned, and in the mean time they ſwell bigger. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs we cannot conceive how flexible <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres</hi> can ſwell bigger, and be ſhortn'd, at the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:51501:39"/> ſame time, but by the means of ſome Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor which fills a Cavity that pierces them from one end to the other.</p>
               <p>After this it will not be very hard to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover how all theſe things muſt act. Each <hi>Tendinous Fibre</hi> receives a Branch of a <hi>Nerve;</hi> and each branch of the <hi>Nerve</hi> ſheds animal Spirits into the Cavity of the <hi>Tendinous Fibre.</hi> The Animal Sprits are the moſt ſubtil and the moſt agitated parts of the Blood. When they enter into the Cavity of the <hi>Tendinous Fibres</hi> they blow them up and ſhorten them. Even as the Air which is blown into a bladder, ſwells it and ſhortens it at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>If we conſider after this, that the Belly of the <hi>Muſcle</hi> is ſtuff'd throughout with <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries</hi> and <hi>Veins,</hi> we will grant that the <hi>Tendinous Fibres</hi> cannot be blown up without diminiſhing the Cavities of the <hi>Arteries</hi> and <hi>Veins,</hi> from whence if fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that the Blood is driven out of them. It is for this that in ſome Animals the <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> become white alwayes when the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Spirits do dilate the <hi>Tendinous Fibres.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:51501:40"/>
               <p>If in fine, we take notice that when the Blood ſtops in the <hi>Arteries</hi> and <hi>Veins,</hi> the <hi>Tendinous Fibres</hi> do not receive enough or motion from the Animal Spirits to thruſt forward that Bloud which ſtayes amongſt them. From hence it follows, that in ſuch rencounters they cannot dilate nor become ſhorter.</p>
               <p>From hence we may conclude, that there are two things abſolutly neceſſary for the blowing up of the <hi>Tendinous Fibres</hi> of the <hi>Muſcles.</hi> the firſt is, that the <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Spirits</hi> muſt have their free courſe through the <hi>Nerve</hi> which goes to the <hi>Muſcle.</hi> For ſince the <hi>Tendinous Fibres</hi> are not blown up but by them, it is clear, that if their courſe be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> interrupted that they cannot flow into their Cavity, they cannot dilate them. Experience confirms this, in that if you cut or tie a <hi>Nerve</hi> with a threed, the <hi>Muſcle</hi> which receives bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches from it, becomes flaccid, and do what you will its <hi>Fibres</hi> do not ſwell.</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing needfull for the blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the <hi>Fibres,</hi> is the free courſe of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:51501:40"/> the Blood through the <hi>Arteries</hi> and <hi>Veins</hi> of the <hi>Muſcles.</hi> For ſince the <hi>Tendinous Fibres</hi> cannot be dilated without ſtraitning the <hi>Arteries</hi> and <hi>Veins,</hi> and the <hi>Arteries</hi> and <hi>Veins</hi> cannot be ſtraitned without void<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Blood that fills them, it is viſible that if the Blood ſtop there, it will hinder the <hi>Tendinous Fibres</hi> from being blown up.</p>
               <p>This is ſo true, that if you take a living Animal and tie the <hi>Aorta</hi> four Fingers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Heart, it becomes paralytick from the ligature even to the Extremities of the feet.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Fibres</hi> of a <hi>Muſcle</hi> are blown up by the Animal Spirits, there are two powers which concur to reſtore them to their firſt eſtate. The firſt is the ſpring which theſe <hi>Fibres</hi> make. For ſince their <hi>Pores</hi> acquire an diſpoſition by their being blown up, the Aetherial matter which does inceſſantly paſs through them, makes an effort to reſtore them to their former eſtate.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is the Effort of the <hi>Arterial Blood,</hi> which being pouſſed by the Heart with Vigour, blows up again the <hi>Arteries</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:51501:41"/> and <hi>Veins,</hi> and at the ſame time ſtraitneth the <hi>Tendinous Fibres.</hi> And as the <hi>Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> empty themſelves of Blood when they are ſtraitned by the ſwellling of the <hi>Fibres,</hi> ſo the <hi>Fibres</hi> empty themſelves of the Animal Spirits, when they are put again into their ordinary ſtate, as well by the force of the <hi>Arterial Blood,</hi> as by that of their Spungineſs.</p>
               <p>As to the reſt, the <hi>Tendons</hi> of the <hi>Muſcles</hi> are ordinarly faſtned to ſome <hi>Cartilage,</hi> or to ſome bone. Which is the Cauſe why the ſhortning of the <hi>Tendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Fibres</hi> makes that part move to which the Tendons are faſtned. It is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marked likewiſe, that one of the Tendons is faſtned to an immovable part, and the other to a moveable part; from whence it follows, that when the <hi>Muſcle</hi> is ſhortned the moveable part is drawn towards the immovable.</p>
               <p>But for as much as there is not almoſt any motion in one part which has not its oppoſite motion, ſo there is not almoſt any Muſcle which has not its oppoſite Muſcle.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:51501:41"/> Theſe Muſcles which ſerve thus to make oppoſite Motions, are called <hi>Antagoniſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is to be obſerved, as to the Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt Muſcles, that when the one is ſhortned, the other is extended. For ſince their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is oppoſite, and that that of the one cannot ſubſiſt at the ſame time with that of the other, the ſhortning of the Muſcle which acts, muſt needs produce the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending of its Antagoniſt.</p>
               <p>But for that the ſhortning of one Muſcle draws the Fibres of its Antagoniſt beyond their ordinary length, they muſt needs ſpring back. It is for this reaſon that the action of one Muſcle which has been lengthned by the contracting of its Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt, is done with eaſe enough. For the Tendinous Fibres can be eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted again, however they have been lengthned, though there be few Animal Spirits which flow into their Cavity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the force of the Spirits is augmented by that of the ſpungineſs of the Fibre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="discourse">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:51501:42"/>
               <head>The ſixth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Cartilages, Bones <hi>and</hi> Membranes.</head>
               <p>WE find in the Body of an Animal many parts which ſeem to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the nature of a Bone, and of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Tendons, in that they are not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo hard as the former, and are leſs ſoft than the other. They call them <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt thing which makes me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture that Cartilages are nothing but a compoſure of Tendinous Fibres which are hardned by being repleniſht with Volatile <hi>Alcalies,</hi> is that there is no Cartilage in which many Tendinous Fibres are not loſt. That which makes my conjecture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, is, that we ſee by the eye, that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Cartilages is nothing but a heap of Fibres. And that which puts the thing out of doubt, is, that in young Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals many parts which were Tendinous become at length Cartilaginous; And that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:51501:42"/> we obſerve frequently in old Animals, that certain Tendons are chang'd into Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilages.</p>
               <p>As Tendons are chang'd at length into Cartilages, the Cartilages are likewiſe changed into Bones. If therefore we have concluded the Cartilages were nothing but a compoſure of Tendinous Fibres, for that the Tendons are ſometimes chang'd into Cartilages; we are obliged by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to judge that Bones are nothing but a Compoſure of Tendinous Fibres, which after having been hardned to become Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilages, are afterwards ſo far hardned as to make Bones.</p>
               <p>The Obſervations which are made upon the Bones of <hi>Foetus</hi>'s do demonſtrate this Truth to the Eye. In effect, we obſerve there a great many Tendinous Fibres, and particularly in the Scull. It appears in the beginning, as if it were nothing but a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane compos'd of Tendinous Fibres. It becomes afterwards Cartilaginous, and in fine is chang'd entirely into Bone. After which it cannot be doubted, but that Bones
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:51501:43"/> are a heap of Tendinous Fibres, which are hardned after ſuch a manner, that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the firmneſs of Bone.</p>
               <p>Tendinous Fibres are hardned, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing repleniſht at length with <hi>Volatile Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies.</hi> The Fibres of the Nerves do ſhed into their Cavity Animal Spirits. That which is more ſubtile of them, eſcapes by the Pores, and the groſſer remains. So that at firſt theſe Fibres are filled with <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile Alcalies</hi> and <hi>Volatile Sulphurs.</hi> Whilſt there are Sulphurs there, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear under the form of a Cartilage; but when the Sulphurs are conſumed, whether by nouriſhing the Fibres, or by eſcaping through the Pores, or in ſplitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they appear under the form of Bones.</p>
               <p>From hence it comes that there are no parts in the whole Body of an Animal, from whence we extract ſo much of <hi>Volatile calies</hi> as from Bones.</p>
               <p>In fine, we remark that Bones are all covered over with a Membrane, which they call the <hi>Perioſtium.</hi> This Membrane
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:51501:43"/> is ſo ſtrongly faſtned to the Bone, that in certain places it is impoſſible to ſeparate it, but by cutting or renting of it.</p>
               <p>When we do examine it narrowly, we find three ſorts of parts which enter into its compoſition; to wit, a great many Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous Fibres, many branches of Nerves, and ſome Arteries and Veins. So that after we have duely conſidered all, we find that the <hi>Perioſtium</hi> is nothing elſe but a Web of Tendinous Fibres of the Bone, Nerves, Veins and Arteries.</p>
               <p>And becauſe all the other Membranes have communication with the Bones and with the Tendons of Muſcles, and for that they have Tendinous Fibres, Nerves, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries and Veins, we judge that all the Membranes which are obſerved in a living Body, are nothing but a Texture of Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous Fibres, Arteries, Veins and Nerves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="discourse">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:51501:44"/>
               <head>The ſeventh Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Lymphatick Veſſels, <hi>and of the</hi> Lympha.</head>
               <p>IT is found that from all the Parts of an Animal, certain ſmall Veſſels do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, which the Anatomiſts call <hi>Lympha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> becauſe they are full of a clear and tranſparent Liquor, which they name <hi>Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Membranes which compoſe them are ſo delicate, that they are inviſible when they are not repleniſht. They are inoſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into one another, and ſo compoſe big enough Trunks, which are inſerted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Veins.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which come from the Head, and from the Neck, are inſerted in the Subcla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian, or in the Jugulars. And the moſt part of thoſe which derive their Origine from the Inferiour parts, and from the <hi>Viſcera</hi> of the lower Belly, do diſcharge
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:51501:44"/> themſelves into one Ciſtern plac'd upon the Vertebra's of the Loins, from whence there goes a Veſſel, which after having paſſed over the Vertebra's of the Thorax, does void its Lympha into the Subclavian Vein.</p>
               <p>This Ciſtern is called the <hi>Reſervatory of the Chyle,</hi> becauſe the Chyle which is form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Stomach by the Digeſtion of the Meat, comes thither, and the Veſſel which goes from this Reſervatory is called <hi>Canalis Thoracicus,</hi> becauſe it is found coucht upon the Vertebra's of the Thorax.</p>
               <p>That which is moſt remarkable in theſe Veſſels, is a great quantity of little Valves, which are placed at very ſmall diſtances from one another. They are ſo diſpoſed as that they permit the Lympha eaſily to run towards the Veins, but they hinder it from coming back again, and from flowing towards the parts from whence the Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatick Veſſels do proceed.</p>
               <p>From whence we may certainly conclude that the Lympha does not come from the Veins but from the parts from whence
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:51501:45"/> the Limphatick Veſſels do derive their Origine. Which agrees perfectly with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; for if you tie with a threed any Lymphatick Veſſel, the Limpha does ſo abound between the Ligature and the part from whence the Veſſel comes, that it blows it up prodigiouſly; and is ſo emptied between the Ligature and the Veins whether it is going to diſcharge its ſelf, that there it becomes inviſible. From whence it follows that the uſe of the Lymphatick Veſſels, is, to carry into the Veins the Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha which they have received from all the parts of the living Body.</p>
               <p>Wee have not hitherto diſcovered any Veſſel which brings any thing to the parts of the living Body, but Arteries and Nerves. The Arteries bring Blood and the Nerves Animal Spirits. It muſt needs therefore be, that the Lympha comes either from the Arteries alone, or from the Nerves alone, or from the Arteries and Nerves together. It does not ſeem to come from the Arteries alone; for if you cut the Nerves which go to one part, there does not flow ſo much
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:51501:45"/> Lympha in the beginning, and diminiſhing by little and little, in fine, it ceaſes entirely. Neither does it come from the Nerves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, ſince if you tie the Arteries which carry the Blood to one part, it ceaſes by little and little to furniſh Lympha. It muſt needs be therefore that the Lympha come partly from the Arteries, and partly from the Nerves. And conſequently it muſt be compoſed of a part of the Arterial Blood and of the Animal Spirits.</p>
               <p>The Lymphatick parts which come from the Blood, paſs after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as the particles of the Liquors which flow from the Glandules. For as theſe paſs from the Blood by being engaged in certain Pores of the Arteries, even ſo the Lymphatick particles finding in the Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſmall Holes through which they may paſs, they are engaged in them. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are followed by others which preſs them forwards, they get out and paſs into the Fibres of the parts from whence the Lymphatick Veſſels come.</p>
               <p>Theſe which come from the Nerves do
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:51501:46"/> not get out by this Artifice. The Nerves inſert their Filaments into the Tendinous Fibres of one part, and ſhed the Animal Spirits into their Cavity. The Fibres have Pores through which they eſcape, and mingle themſelves with what runs from the Arteries, to compoſe the Lympha by their mixture.</p>
               <p>Since we have eſtabliſht in the diſcourſe of Nerves that the Animal Spirits are no thing but a Sulphureous Alcalie, we may well think that the Lympha is nothing but a Compoſure of Volatile Sulphurs, Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Alcalies and a little Phlegm. The Volatile Sulphurs, and Volatile Alcalies are the Animal Spirits which enter into its compoſition; and the Phlegm with the fixt Sulphurs are thoſe of its parts which come from the Blood by the Pores of the Arteries.</p>
               <p>An Experiment which ſucceeds always, confirms this Sentiment. That is, if you gather of the Lympha in a Silver Spoon, and place the Spoon on the Fire, as ſoon as it begins to warm, there goes from the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:51501:46"/> Lympha a ſmall Vapour, and then it har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens like the white of an Egg that is boil'd.</p>
               <p>I ſay this Experiment confirms, that the Lympha is nothing but a Compoſure of a great deal of Fixt Sulphur, a little of Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, a little of Phlegme and much Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Alcalie. For the Lympha is fluid, whilſt the Volatile Alcalies keep its Sulphurs diſſolved, and it hardens like the white of an Egg, how ſoon the Fire has exhal'd them. For then the Fixt Sulphurs being alone, do ſo entangle their branches one with another, that they cannot move after the manner that is needful to compoſe a Liquor. As to the Volatile Sulphur and the Phlegme, it cannot be denied but there is of them in the Lympha; for that the Animal Spirits which compoſe a part of it, are made up of them, and the Vapours go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Lympha, when ſet on the Fire, do ſufficiently reſemble the Vapours of Water.</p>
               <p>We conclude from this, that the uſe of the Lympha is to nouriſh the parts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Fibres of which it flows. As
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:51501:47"/> will appear plainly enough after what we are going to ſay of Nutrition.</p>
               <p>It is a truth well enough known, that many Particles of our Bodies are ſeparated and do exhale; and becauſe theſe parts go out by the Pores of the Skin, as if it were a moſt ſubtile Wind, they call this <hi>Tranſpiration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The parts which paſs from our Bodies by Tranſpiration, are ordinarily Salts diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in Phlegmes, with which there are ſome Sulphurs mingled. They are ſeparat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Blood by the means of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of ſmall Glandules, which are ſituated under the Skin, and whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretory Veſſels end at ſmall Holes, which are on the Surface of the Body, and which we call Pores.</p>
               <p>Theſe Glandules which we ſhall call Subcutaneous, do receive Arteries, ſend forth Veins, and have ſome Filaments of Nerves. So that judging of them by others, we may well think that their uſe is, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the Maſſe of Blood the Saline parts, which are formed thereby the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:51501:47"/> of the <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Alcalies.</hi> Which makes us conclude that the parts which paſs away by Tranſpiration, are parts of the Humours of the living Body, and not Particles of its ſolid parts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Acids</hi> which are mingled with the Humours paſs away, not only when they are joyn'd with the <hi>Alcalies,</hi> but alſo when they are joyn'd to the Sulphurs. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Animal Oeconomy,</hi> has put a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of Glandules in the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane, which cover the thin Leafs of Bone in the Noſe, which are proper to ſeparate from the Blood the Sulphurs united with <hi>Acids.</hi> It is for this that there runs from the Noſtrils a Glewy and whitiſh Liquor.</p>
               <p>By this we ſee after what manner the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies, Sulphurs</hi> and <hi>Phlegmes</hi> of our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours are conſum'd. Which makes us think that they would be very ſoon ſpent entirely, if they were not repair'd. And it is this reparation of the Humours which we call <hi>Nutrition</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Animal Body is never better nouriſht, than when all its parts are full of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:51501:48"/> Humours which Circulate, or are in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And becauſe it is the Lympha which flows amongſt the Fibres of the ſolid parts and fill up their Interſtices, it is this alſo which is that Humour whoſe abundance makes Nouriſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="discourse">
               <head>The eight Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Mouth.</head>
               <p>EVery Body knows, that the Mouth is that Cavity which all Animals have in their head; and through which the Aliments do enter into their Body. In it four principal things are taken notice of; which are, the Teeth, the Palat, the Spittle and the Tongue.</p>
               <p>But before wee enter to enquire into theſe things, it will not be impertinent to remark, that the Mouth is made by the upper and the under jaws. The moſt part of Animals open the Mouth by putting down the nether Jaw, and they ſhut it
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:51501:48"/> by taking it up. The Contrary is obſerved in Crocodiles, Serpents, and Lizards.</p>
               <p>The ſides of the Jaws are pierced with many Holes of a good depth. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive into their Cavities the roots of thoſe little Bones, which are more poliſht, more white and hard than others, which adorn the entry of the Mouth like to a Paliſſade, and are called <hi>Teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That part of the Teeth which enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Holes of the Jaws, is called their <hi>Root,</hi> and that which ſtands out is chiefly nam'd the <hi>Teeth.</hi> The Roots are uſually much longer than the Teeth themſelves, which is the Cauſe that they keep firm to the Jaws.</p>
               <p>Some have their Roots with three points, others of them with two, there are many of them alſo which have but one. When wee break the Teeth with a Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, wee find in the Body of them an empty Cavity, which extends its ſelf even to the Root.</p>
               <p>The Teeth are not only fixt to the Jaws by their Root, but they are likewiſe faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:51501:49"/> to them by a hard and firm Fleſh which covers their ſides, and whoſe Fibres are extended from one end of the Jaws to the other. This Fleſh is called the <hi>Gums.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover the Teeth are of three ſorts. Thoſe which are plac'd in the entry of the Mouth are broad, and their extremities made with an edge. They are called <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Inciſivi.</hi> The other which are farther within the Mouth, and which the Cheeks cover have a thick, ſtrong and large Body, and their extremities broad and unequall, which makes them fit to break and bruiſe. It is for this they call them <hi>Dentes Molares,</hi> or the <hi>Grinders.</hi> And there are yet others which are very ſtrong, and have their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities pointed, and are moſt fit to hold any thing faſt. There is alwayes one of them plac'd on each ſide, between the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſive and the Grinders, and they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Dog-Teeth</hi> or <hi>Eye-Teeth,</hi> becauſe they receive a branch of a Nerve from thoſe which move the eye.</p>
               <p>The number of the Teeth is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the ſame. Some men have 14 in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:51501:49"/> each Jaw, ſome have 15 and others 16. Uſually they reckon four Inciſive, two Dog-Teeth, and eight Grinders, as well in the upper as the neather Jaw.</p>
               <p>From all this we may Conclude, that the Teeth ſerve to chew the Aliment. The Inciſive cut it into little Morſels, and the Grinders break and bruiſe it into very ſmall peices, to the end it may paſs forwards, and the Dog-Teeth cut it in peices, when the Inciſive are not ſtrong enough for this effect.</p>
               <p>The Palate is that part of the Mouth which makes its Roof, and which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended from the upper Jaw-bone even to the bottom of the Mouth. The ſurface of it is unequal, and its Fore-part cut into ſmall narrow ſurrows, plac'd near one another, from the Inciſive Teeth to the middle of the Mouth and its hinder part is of a pretty even ſurface</p>
               <p>It is furniſht outwardly with a very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Coat, under which there is another more thick and ſtrong, when this is raiſed wee diſcover an almoſt infinite number of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:51501:50"/> ſmall Glandules. Theſe, being form'd like the Grapes of Raiſins make up the Body of the ſurrows of the Palate. Their Excretory Veſſels do pierce the membrane which covers the membrane which covers the furrows, and ſhed into the Mouth a pretty clear and ſomewhat viſcuous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor. The hinder part of the Palat, whoſe ſurface is even, hath under its membranes ſmall Glandules of the bigneſs of the Grains of Millet. They differ from thoſe which make the furrows of the Fore-part in this, that they are not ranked about their Excretory Veſſels, as the Grains of Raiſins about the ſtalk of the Grape: but they peirce the Membranes of the Palate by as many Excretory Veſſels, as there are Glandules. All theſe Glandules of the Palate receive Arteries from the Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tides, ſend Veins to the external Jugulars, and receive Filaments of Nerves from the ſeventh pair.</p>
               <p>We find at the bottom of the Palate three remarkable Bodies, to wit, two Glandules, on each ſide one. They call
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:51501:50"/> them the <hi>Almonds;</hi> and between theſe Glandules a ſmall piece of Fleſh of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Figure, which they call the <hi>Avula</hi> or <hi>Pape.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Almonds are Veſiculate Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules of a Yellowiſh colour. Though they ſeem two in number, yet they are but one, the middle of which is covered by the Membrane of the Palate, and the Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities appear like two Lobes. This middle part which makes the Communication of the two Lobes, is both more ſtrait and more delicate, than the two ends of this Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule.</p>
               <p>Each Lobe has a <hi>Sinus</hi> or Cavity, which is divided in many Appartments, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretory Veſſels of theſe ſmall Veſicles tend thither, and ſhed a glewy and whitiſh Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, which is not unlike to the Snot of the Noſe. They receive Arteries from the Vertebrals, they ſend Veins to the Jugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and their Nerves come from the third, fourth, and fifth pair.</p>
               <p>As for the Uvula, it is nothing but a ſmall bag of the Membrane of the Palate.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:51501:51"/> It hangs between the two Lobes, which make the Almonds. This Bag is full of an infinite number of ſmall Veſicular Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules, which are of the colour of the Fleſh, becauſe of the great number of Arteries which they receive from the Vertebrals and the Carotides, and the many Veins which they ſend to the Jugulars Their Excretory Veſſels do peirce on all ſides its outward Membrane, and bedew it with a Tranſparent &amp; ſomewhat viſcuous Liquor.</p>
               <p>The Mouth is not only watered with the Liquor which flows from the Glandules of the Palate and the Uvula, there are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe four other great ſtreams which empty themſelves into it. They diſcharge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of a ſweet and Tranſparent Water, in which there is ſome Viſcoſity remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. This Liquor is called the <hi>Spittie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We find within the Mouth two ſmall Holes, the one on the Right, the other on the Left ſide. They peirce the Checks to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Molar Teeth, or Grinders: And becauſe we find them alwayes wet, we make no doubt but they are the opening of two ſtreams of Spittle.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:51501:51"/>
               <p>And indeed if we put into them a Bod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, we find that it goes without difficulty into a ſmall Membranous Pipe, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends its ſelf alongſt the Cheeks, and is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into many ſmall Branches when it approaches below the Ear. This Veſſel is always found full of Spittle, and the ſmall Branches which are at its riſe, do loſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a heap of Vaſcular Glandules. Theſe Glandules are placed about the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-part of the Ear, they are called <hi>Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tides.</hi> So that the ſmall Excretory Veſſels which go from each Glandule coming to be inoſculated together, make up Veſſels ſomewhat larger. Theſe larger Veſſels joyning together do compoſe a greater, which encreaſeth according as it approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Mouth, where it empties the Spittle which the Parotides have ſeparated from the Blood.</p>
               <p>Moreover the Parotides do receive their Arteries from the Carotides, and ſend Veins to the External Jugulars; there are amongſt them many Branches of Nerves which come from the hard portion of the ſeventh pair.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:51501:52"/>
               <p>The opening of the two other ſtreams which do diſcharge the Spittle into the Mouth, is to be ſeen under the point of the Tongue towards the inciſive Teeth. They are ſo ſmall that they cannot admit a Hogs Briſtle. They appear at the end of two fleſhy <hi>Papillae,</hi> which ſerve them for ſmall Sphincters. They extend themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longſt the Tongue, and when they come near its root, they are divided into many Branches which loſe themſelves in a heap of Glandules, which are called the <hi>Maxil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Glandules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are placed within the under Jaw, and they extend themſelves from the root of the Tongue even to the Chin. The part of this Conglomerated Glandule which comes neareſt unto the Parotides, is groſſer and more red than the reſt. As it advanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth towards the Chin, it diminiſheth, ſo that it becomes by little and little more narrow and ſlender. There is remarked towards its middle part a little ſtrait, which joyns its fore part to the hinder. And afterwards, after having encreaſed conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:51501:52"/> it extends its ſelf even to the Chin, under the Figure of a Quince.</p>
               <p>All the Glandules which compoſe it are nothing but a Convolution of Veſſels, which are Inoſculated in one another to make by their Concourſe two conſiderable Canals. Theſe Canals extend themſelves on each ſide, on the ſide of the Tongue, and end at the two <hi>Papillae</hi> faſtned to the Gums, near the two inciſive Teeth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Mouth.</p>
               <p>The Maxillar Glandules receive their Arteries from the Carotides, they ſend Veins to the Jugulars, their Nerves come cheifly from the third, fourth, and ſeventh pair. They ſeparate from the Blood the ſpittle, and the Veſſels of which wee have been ſpeaking do empty it in the Mouth.</p>
               <p>Beſides the four ſtreams of ſpittle, we remark alſo many ſmall Rivulets of it which are within the under Lip and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longſt the Gum on the inſide of the Mouth. It comes from ſome Glandules which are found engaged amongſt the Carneous Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of theſe parts, and whoſe Excretory
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:51501:53"/> Veſſels pour into the Mouth the Liquor which they have ſeparated from the Blood.</p>
               <p>The little Viſcoſity that is remarked in the Spittle makes us think that it is compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſome Sulphurs, ſome acids and much Phlegms with which there are ſome Salts. It mingles with the Aliments in the Mouth, and facilitates the Chewing by Moiſtning of them. It renders them more fluid, and by conſequent fitter to paſs through the Conduits which muſt carry them elſewhere. It may be ſaid alſo that by its acids and ſalts, it opens their ſmall parts and makes the beginning of a diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. The Sulphurs enwrap its acids by a marvellous precaution of the Author of the <hi>Animal Oeconomy,</hi> to the end they may not corrode the parts which muſt be watered with Spittle.</p>
               <p>The neceſſity of the mixture of Spittle with the Aliments appears in that all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs to make it. The Aliments preſs the Palate, and ſo oblige the Spittle which its Glandules contain, to run into the Mouth, by the little Excretory Veſſels, which
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:51501:53"/> peirce its Membrane. The Crotaphite Muſcle and the Maſſeters, by ſtraitning and dilating themſelves preſs the Parotides, and through their Veſſels make two little ſtreams of Spittle to run which enter on the right and left Side into the Mouth. The Digaſtrick by its contraction and dilatation agitates the Maxillar Glandules, and preſſes the Spittle out of them, which runs through their Excretory Veſſels like two little ſtreams, which diſcharge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Mouth. And whereas in the time of chewing all theſe parts play to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether after the manner we have ſaid, it muſt needs be granted that this mixture of the Spittle with the Aliments is moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
               <p>In fine, we muſt examine the Tongue, which is a peice of Fleſh almoſt of a Coni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Figure. Its Baſis is faſtned unto the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Mouth by a little Bone which they call <hi>Os Hyoides.</hi> And from its Baſis even to the middle it is faſtned by its under part to the Muſcles, which fill the Cavity of the Under-Jaw, ſo that its point is free, and does not cleave to any part.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:51501:54"/>
               <p>Under the free part of the Tongue there is a ſmall Line made of ſmall Tendinous Fibres, which reach from one end, even to the place where the Tongue ceaſeth to cleave to the parts which fill the Cavity of the Under Jaw. This ſmall Line is called the <hi>Bridle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hyoides Bone is plac'd in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Mouth at the Baſis of the Tongue. It has the Figure of a very open Fork, whoſe Arms cleave to an heap of Cartilages, which they call the <hi>Larynx.</hi> It is compoſed of many little Bones, which are joyn'd by Cartilaginous knots. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there are but three of them, and at other times they reckon thirteen, to wit, ſix on each ſide. As for the Bone in the midſt to which the Tongue is faſtned, it is big in compare with the reſt, which are very ſlender, It is likewiſe ſomewhat broad, bunching towards the Tongue and hollow towards the Larynx. On its raiſed ſide it has two ſmall appendages which are ordinarily Cartilaginous. They call them the <hi>Horns of the Bone Hyoides.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:51501:54"/>
               <p>There are five pairs of Muſcles which do make it move with the Tongue. The firſt is the <hi>Genthoidien</hi> which has its riſe from within the Chin, and reaches to the Baſis of the Bone Hyoides. Theſe Muſcles ſerve to raiſe it by the ſhortning of their Fibres. The ſecond is the <hi>Sternohoïdien.</hi> It comes from the top of the <hi>Sternum,</hi> aſcends alongſt the <hi>Arteria Trachaea,</hi> and is faſtned to the Baſis of the Os Hyoides. This pair of Muſcles draws it downwards. The third is the <hi>Milohyoïdien.</hi> It ariſes from within the Under Jaw towards the Hammers, and is inſerted into the Baſis of the Os Hyoides, which draws it up taking it by the ſides. The fourth pair is the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racohyïdien.</hi> It comes from the Cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coide Apophyſis of the Omoplate. Theſe have two Bellies, and are inſerted into the Horns of the of Hyoides, which they draw downwards, taking it by the ſides. The fifth is the <hi>Stilo Ceratohyoïdien.</hi> It ariſeth from the Apophyſis Stiloïdes, and is inſerted into the Horns of the Os Hyoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: Theſe Muſcles reſtore it to its ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:51501:55"/> Situation, when it has been mov'd by others. They are peirced to give paſſage to the Digaſtrique.</p>
               <p>As for the Tongue, it is covered with an outer Membrane, which may be taken for the Cuticula. We find under it a ſubſtance which ſeems Viſcuous. It is moderately thick, white on the ſide that touches the outer Membrane, and black on the other. They call it the <hi>Reticular Body.</hi> This Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Body is peirced like to a Sieve, and there ariſeth from each of its Holes ſmall Conical Bodies of a pretty hard Subſtance. They appear in an extraordinary manner on the Tongue of Cats. They are very long and crooked towards the point of the Tongue, like ſo manny little Horns. We remark them alſo on the Tongues of Oxen and of other Animals of the ſame bigneſs. When thoſe ſmall Conical Bodies are pluck'd off, they leave conſiderable Holes in the Reticular Body, and their covers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the outer Surface of the Tongue.</p>
               <p>Under the Reticular Body, there is a Coat woven of Tendinous Fibres, and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laments
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:51501:55"/> of Nerves of the fifth, and ninth pair, upon which appears a prodigious quantity of ſmall Nervous Papillae. Each of theſe Papillae is covered with one of thoſe Conical Bodies of which we have ſpoken. They peirce the Reticular Body, and terminate upon the Surface of the Tongue.</p>
               <p>Upon the Tongues of men there are none of thoſe Conical Bodies which are chiefly remarked on the Tongues of four-footed Animals. But the Papillae paſs even to the outer Coat of the Tongue, which they elevate in little heights, and thereby render its Surface very unequal.</p>
               <p>They reckon three kinds of Papillae both on the Tongues of men and on thoſe of Oxen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The firſt are made like to the Horns of Snails, they have on the top a ſmall round head. They are not numerous, ſome are placed on the ſides of the point of the Tongue; there are none of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and many of them are found on the ſide of its Baſis. The ſecond are divided into ſmall Fibres, which loſe themſelves
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:51501:56"/> in the riſings of the outer Coat of the Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, and they are plac'd on its upper part. The Third are Conical and wee find then, placed confuſedly amongſt the reſt. They riſe all from the Papillar Bodies, they peirce the Reticular Body, and go to the outer Membrane of the Tongue, which they elevate in heights in men, and there they rencounter the roots of the Conical Bodies in Oxen and other Animals which have them.</p>
               <p>In fine, the Tongue has five orders of Fibres by which it makes all its motions, beſides thoſe which are performed by the Muſcles of the Os Hyoides. The firſt is of thoſe which are extended in a ſtraight, line from its Baſis to its point, paſſing through the middle of its Body: by their Contraction they ſerve to draw its point towards the Baſe. The ſecond is of theſe which paſſing from its Baſe even to its point, do furniſh its two ſides. By their Contraction, they move the Tongue to the right and left. The third is of thoſe which paſſing from one ſide to the other,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:51501:56"/> are interlaced with the firſt and cut them at right Angles. When they are ſhortned they make the Tongue round. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears much more towards the point of the Tongue than elſewhere. The fourth is of thoſe which coming from its Baſis do embrace a part of the Tongue; they are interlaced with the Fibres of the firſt and third Order, cutting them obliquely. The effect which the ſhortning of them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth, is that they draw the Tongue backward, without ſhortning it conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably. And the fifth is a few Fibres which derive their Origin from the Chin, and are inſerted into the under part of the Tongue; they aſcend even pretty far into its Body. When they are ſhortned, they draw the Tongue without the Mouth.</p>
               <p>Towards the Baſe of the Tongue, we remark many ſmall Glandules, ſituated amongſt its Fibres. They have Excreto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Veſſels, which yield Spittle into the Mouth, and whoſe Orifices do appear in many places of its Surface. Beſides theſe, there are likewiſe ſome others obſerved
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:51501:57"/> ſituated on the ſides of the Tongue, they call them <hi>Sublinguales.</hi> They have many Excretory Veſſels, whoſe Orifices do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear on the Gums towards the Hammers. There runs from them, as from the reſt a clear Tranſparent, and ſomewhat viſcuous Liquor.</p>
               <p>The Fibres of the Tongue do ſhew us that its uſe is to agitate the Meat in the Mouth, and to make it paſs by its diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent motions, ſometimes under the Grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be divided and broken. And as by all theſe motions it ſtrikes the Palate, agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates the Maxillar Glandules, and that its proper Glandules are preſt from time to time, it obliges all its Glandules to yield a conſiderable quantity of Spittle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Mouth. So that it is a great Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chewing.</p>
               <p>And in fine, when it is drawn back and raiſed at the ſame time by the Muſcles of the Os Hyoides, it preſſes the Meat into a Conduit, called the <hi>Oeſophagus,</hi> which comes to the Cavity of the Mouth, and by this means ſerves to the ſwallowing of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="discourse">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:51501:57"/>
               <head>The Ninth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Oeſophagus.</head>
               <p>WHen we trace the Aliments, we find that they go from the Mouth into a Conduit which is extended alongſt the Neck and Breaſt, peirces the Diaphtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma and is inſerted into the Stomach. They call it the <hi>Oeſophagus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is very true that the Aliments paſs over a Cartilage, which covers the Orifice of a Pipe that enters into the Breaſt. This Cartilage is ordinarily lifted up, and the Aliments put it down, when they are thruſt by the Tongue into the Oeſophagus They call it the <hi>Epiglottis.</hi> But becauſe the Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments paſs over it, without ſtopping there, and it has no uſe as to them, we ſhall not ſtop at it here, but ſhall reſerve to ſpeak of it in another place.</p>
               <p>After the Epiglottis the Orifice of the Oeſophagus appears which they call the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:51501:58"/> 
                  <hi>Pharinx.</hi> It is ordinarily ſhut, and does not open but to give paſſage to what is thruſt forward that way by the Tongue, or to let out what is voided by the Stomach into the Mouth.</p>
               <p>It opens and ſhuts as is needfull, by the help of ſeven Muſcles. The firſt is called <hi>Oeſophagian.</hi> It is ſtrongly faſtned to the two ſides of the Scutiform Cartilage, and covers the Oeſophagus by its Circuit. Its uſe is to ſhut the entry of the Oeſopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus.</p>
               <p>The others are double. The firſt are called <hi>Sphaenopharingians.</hi> They derive their origine from within the ſharp Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſes of the Os Sphaenoides; and are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely inſerted in the ſides of the <hi>Pharinx,</hi> which they open by drawing it upwards.</p>
               <p>The ſecond are the <hi>Stilopharingians.</hi> They ariſe from the extremity of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſes Stiloides</hi> of the Bones of the Temples, and are inſerted into the ſides of the <hi>Pharinx,</hi> which they dilate by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its ſides to the right and left Hand.</p>
               <p>The third are the <hi>Cephalopharingians.</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:51501:58"/> They derive their Origine from the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of the Head with the firſt Verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra, and ſpread their Fibres into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the <hi>Pharinx,</hi> which they ſhut by the ſhortning of their Fibres.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the <hi>Oeſophagus</hi> extends its ſelf in a ſtraight line from the <hi>Pharinx</hi> to the Stomach. It is compoſed of three Coats, which may be called, the inner, the middle, and the outer Coat, The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is made up of nothing but Tendinous Fibres diverſly interlaced. The middle is made up of Carneous Fibres, of which they reckon two Orders, both in Men and in other Animals. In Men the Fibres of the firſt Order reach alongſt from the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinx</hi> to the Stomach, for which cauſe they are named <hi>Longitudinal Fibres;</hi> and thoſe of the ſecond Order are like to ſo many little Circles which do encircle the <hi>Oeſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phagus,</hi> above which the Longitudinals are placed. They are called <hi>Circular.</hi> In Animals, which eat with the Head down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, they have another Poſition. The two Orders of Fibres go ſpirally round
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:51501:59"/> about the Oeſophagus. And for as much as the one go from the right to the left, whilſt the others paſs from the left to the right, they do in many places paſs one above another. There is ſomewhat ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular in this paſſing, to wit. That the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres which paſs in one place above others, do go under them at the next rencounter, at the ſecond they aſcend above: And in fine, they paſs again under them. The outer Coat is compoſed of Tendinous Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, more ſubtil and ſlender than thoſe of the Inner. The inner and outer Coat ſerve for Tendons to the middle. So that we may conſider the <hi>Oeſophagus</hi> as a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, whoſe inner Coat is the Head, the middle the Belly, and the outer Coat the Tail. So that in Men the <hi>Oeſophagus</hi> is ſhortned by the ſwelling of the Longitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Fibres. And it is ſtraitned by the ſhortning of the Circular. They call that ſhortning and this contraction of the <hi>Oeſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phagus</hi> its <hi>Periſtaltique Motion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Beaſts, the ſhortning and contraction of the <hi>Oeſophagus</hi> is much greater than in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:51501:59"/> Men, for that the Muſculous Fibres de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend ſpirally and do croſs one another, For when they ſwell, and by conſequent are ſhortned, whileſt they thereby ſhorten the <hi>Oeſophagus,</hi> they make its Cavity leſs, becauſe by their Action they wreath it.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Periſtaltick</hi> motion is made to the end that what has once paſt the <hi>Pharinx</hi> may not ſtop in the Cavity of the <hi>Oeſopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus.</hi> So that we may well affirm, that the <hi>Oeſophagus</hi> is fram'd after this manner, to thruſt the Meat forward by its Periſtaltick motion, even into the Stomach.</p>
               <p>In Beaſts the Periſtaltick motion of the <hi>Oeſophagus</hi> ſtraitens its Cavity much more than in Men, for that they Eat or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarly with their Head downward. There is therefore more force needful to make the Meat aſcend through the Oeſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phagus, that it may go into the Stomach.</p>
               <p>In fine, this Periſtaltick motion is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Vermicular,</hi> becauſe the Oeſophagus moves as Worms do, by ſtraitning and ſhortning its ſelf in one place, and ſwelling
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:51501:60"/> in another, which is continued from one of its ends even to the other by Undulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The cauſe of this may be, that the Filaments of the Nerves do enter oblique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Tendinous Fibres of the Coats. For as ſoon as the Animal Spirits were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into one Fibre, they would be ſhut up by blowing up the end of the Nervous Filament from whence they come. And ſo ſhutting the door upon others, they would hinder more from flowing in, till the Fibres were reſtored to their former Eſtate by the force of their ſpring. And in as much as the Longitudinal Fibres are all of a piece, and the circular ones com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate all together by the ſmall Tendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Fibres, the animal Spirits paſſing farther into the Longitudinals, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the neighbour circular ones, they would produce there the ſame effect which they had done in the former. So that continuing to run thus from the one end of the Oeſophagus to the other, they would produce a Vermicular or Undulating mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which one place becomes more
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:51501:60"/> ſtraitned and ſhortned, then is reſtored in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its former eſtate, whileſt this ſtraitning and ſhortning deſcends farther, and ſo of the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="discourse">
               <head>The tenth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Stomach, <hi>and of</hi> Chylification.</head>
               <p>THe Oeſophagus is inſerted into a kind of bag made almoſt like a Bag-pipe; and this they call the <hi>Stomach.</hi> It is ſhort and open at both ends. The place where the Oeſophagus joyns it, is on the left ſide, they call it the upper Orifice of the Stomach; and the other place where it is open, which is on the right, is called the <hi>Pylorus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The inner Coat of the Oeſophagus lyes within cloſe about the upper orifice for the ſpace of three inches.</p>
               <p>Wee find that the Stomach is made up of three Coats, the outer and inner are woven of Tendinous Fibres, and the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:51501:61"/> is made of Carneous Fibres. All be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the inner Tunicle and the middle is repleniſht with ſmall Veſicular Glandules. Their Excretory Veſſels peirce the inner Tunicle &amp; form in its Cavity a ſmall down, for which they call it the <hi>Velvet Tunicle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When wee examine the Compoſition of the middle Coat we find ordinarly three orders of Fibres in Beaſts, and two in Men. The firſt is nothing but the continuation of the Longitudinal Fibres of the Oeſopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, which extend themſelves from the upper Orifice of the Stomach even to the Pylorus. And the other is nothing but the Continuation of the Circular Fibres of the Oeſophagus, which are cut by the Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitudinals at right Angles. Thus it is that they are in men In Dogs, Cats &amp;c. Beſides theſe two orders of Longitudinal and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Fibres, there are two handfuls of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres extremely cloſe, which extend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the right and left above the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, from its upper Orifice even to the Pilorus. They are nothing but the Spiral Fibres of the Oeſophagus which are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:51501:61"/> into two handfuls at the upper Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and parting the one from the other, they paſs alongſt above the Stomach and are reunited at the Pylorus.</p>
               <p>All theſe different orders of Fibres are made to produce a Periſtaltick motion in the Stomach. It is by the means of this motion that the Aliments which enter into the Stomach by its upper Orifice, are ſent out by the Pylorus.</p>
               <p>Morover the Stomach receives Arteries from the Caeliack, ſends Veins to the Sple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick and to the <hi>Vena Porta,</hi> the <hi>Parvagum</hi> does furniſh it two branches of Nerves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable enough, and many Nervous Fila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments come from the Meſenterical Plexus: and in fine it gives riſe to ſome Lympha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Veſſels which go into the Reſervatory of the Chyle.</p>
               <p>There would be nothing more to be ſaid of the Stomach, if we did not obſerve that the Aliments contract a conſiderable change during the ſtay they make there. In effect it is obſerved that they become Liquid and of a whitiſh colour. This Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:51501:62"/> is called the <hi>Chyle,</hi> and the action that produced it is nam'd <hi>Chylification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To begin to examine the nature of Chyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. I obſerve that it produceth fluidity in the Aliments which were ſolid. Wee have learned in the Phyſicks that Fluidity conſiſts in the diviſion and various motion of the Particles of fluid Bodies. So that by Chylification the parts of the Aliments muſt be ſeparated from one another and diverſly moved.</p>
               <p>This ſeparation of the parts of the Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cannot be done but by bruiſing or by Fermentation. We know nothing in the Stomach that can ſo perfectly break and grind the Aliments as is needfull to change them into Chyle. We muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude then, that this Separation of the parts of the Aliments is made by Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>We have remarked in our Diſcourſe of the Elements of the living Body, that Fermentation is not made, but by the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of two Bodies of a different nature, and that it is done for the moſt part by the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:51501:62"/> mixture of Acids and Alcalies. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, ſince Alcalies are needful to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Sulphurs, Phlegmes to diſſolve Salts, and Acids to diſſolve Alcalies, we cannot affirm that the Ferment which by its mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture makes the diſſolution of the Aliments in the Stomach, is only an Acid, an Alcali, or a Phlemge; ſeing by Chylification, both Salts, Sulphurs and Alcalies are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
               <p>But the Ferment muſt be compoſed of Principles capable of making a Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which diſſolves Sulphurs, Alcalies and Salts. And ſince we have eſtabliſh'd that Alcalies diſſolve Sulphurs, Acids Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calies. and Phlegmes Salts, we muſt of neceſſity conclude that the Ferment of Chylification, is a compoſure of Acid, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cali and Phlegme.</p>
               <p>If the Ferment of the Stomach be ſuch, as ſoon as the Elements ſhall begin to mingle with it, its Acids will act upon their Alcalies, and by the Fermentation which they ſhall excite with them, will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to diſſolve the whole Maſſe of the Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:51501:63"/> The Alcalies of the Ferment coming afterwards to paſs amongſt the Sulphureous parts of the Aliment, will keep them ſeparated from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>And in fine, the Phlegmes after having diſſolved the Salts, will find place amongſt all the parts of the Aliments, whoſe union will be broken by the Action of the Acids, and Alcalies.</p>
               <p>Some difficulty may be raiſed upon what we have ſaid, that the Ferment of the Stomach was compoſed of Acid and Alcali; for that theſe two Principles can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubſiſt together without a Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which would change them imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately into Salt. But if we conſider, that certain Acids may have their Angles very pointed, and the ſides of theſs Angles very ſlender, and that the Pores of an Alcali may be large enough to let the Aetherial matter paſs through, though an Angle of theſe Acids be thruſt in there, we will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comprehend after what manner an Acid may be mingled with an Alcalie without
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:51501:63"/> exciting Fermentation, and without unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſely with it. For in this caſe there will be Intervals large enough between the Concavity of the Pores of the Alcalies, and the ſides of the points of the Acids which are placed there, to give paſſage to the matter which flows through their Pores. And ſince it is the obſtacle which this Aetherial matter meets with in its paſſage, which makes it ſeparate the parts of Bodies, it is clear that it needs not here produce any Fermentation.</p>
               <p>When therefore the Aliments deſcend into the Stomach by their weight, the preſs the ſmall Glandules, which are placed between its inner and middle Coats. Since they are nothing but little Veſicles, ſo ſoon as they are preſt they empty them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and Diſtil into the Cavity of the Stomach, a ſufficient dew of Ferment, which mingles with what is found there, Ferments it, diſſolves it, and makes it Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid.</p>
               <p>That which is Liquified gets above and obeying the Periſtaltique motion of the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:51501:64"/> Stomach goes out by the Pylorus. So long as this Fermentation laſts there goes away alwayes ſomewhat of this ſort, and when it is finiſhed the Animal muſt eat or he is expoſed to hunger, which proceeds from this that the Ferment being altogether pure in the Stomach it frets the inward Tunicle.</p>
               <p>The Ferment of the Aliments does ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver entirely diſſolve the parts, there are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſome of them which eſcape it. This is the Cauſe that the Chyle is not to be met with at the going out of the Stomach, and that it is mingled with many groſs and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs parts. It is for this reaſon that nature has made the Chyle to paſs through a long Pipe of Inteſtins, in which it is mingled in divers places with different Liquors, which ſerve to ſeparate what is good from what might be hurtful to the conſervation of the living Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="discourse">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:51501:64"/>
               <head>The Eleventh Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Inteſtines.</head>
               <p>THe Chyle in going out of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach paſſes into a Conduit join'd to the Pylorus, which is called the <hi>Guts,</hi> or <hi>Intestines.</hi> This Conduit makes many Circumvolutions: And in fine, after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made many windings, terminates in the Fundament.</p>
               <p>They divide them into ſix parts, to which they give different Names. The firſt, which they call the <hi>Duodenum,</hi> begins at the Pylorus, and ends at a place where a yellowiſh and oleous Liquor is diſcharged into the Cavity of the Inteſtines. It is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narly repleniſhed with the Chyle ſuch as it comes from the Stomach.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, which is uſually found almoſt empty, is called <hi>Intestinum Jeju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> It begins at the end of the Duode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, and ends at the places where we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:51501:65"/> to find Excrements. They give it the length of ten or twelve Palms. The third is called the <hi>Ilium.</hi> It begins at the end of the <hi>Jejunum,</hi> and ends at th ſmall end of a Gut, which is faſtned unto the Cavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the reſt, like the bottom of a Sack. Hitherto the Inteſtines are very delicate and their Cavity ſmall enough: And it is for this they are called the <hi>ſmall Inteſtines.</hi> The fourth is called the <hi>Caecum,</hi> which is the ſmall end of a Gut faſtned to the reſt, of which we have made mention. The fifth is called the <hi>Colum.</hi> It begins at the <hi>Caecum,</hi> and makes a great Circuit about the other Guts: We find at its entry a Membranous folding, whis is ſo framed, that it permits the Excrements to paſs eaſily from the <hi>Ilium</hi> to the <hi>Colum,</hi> but does not ſuffer them to paſs without dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty from the <hi>Colum</hi> to the <hi>Ilium.</hi> The Cavity of the <hi>Colum</hi> is all divided into little Cells, and it ends at the place where the reſt of the Guts goes ſtraight to the Fundament. This makes the ſixth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine, which is called <hi>Rectum</hi> The
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:51501:65"/> 
                  <hi>Caecum,</hi> the <hi>Colum,</hi> and the <hi>Rectum,</hi> are called the <hi>Great Inteſtines,</hi> becauſe their Coats are ſtronger and groſſer than thoſe of the ſmall Inteſtines.</p>
               <p>All the Inteſtines are made up of three Tunicles, as, the Oeſophagus of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. The inner is a Texture of Tendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Fibres diverſly interlac'd; the middle has two Orders of Carneous Fibres, of which the one are Circular, and the other Longitudinal: And the outer is a Texture of Tendinous Fibres. Theſe Tunicles ſerve to make the Periſtaltick motion of the Inteſtines, after the ſame manner that it is done in the Oeſophagus and the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. This Vermicular motion ſerves to make that which is in the Inteſtines to paſs even to the Fundament, that it may be thrown out of the Body as uſeleſs.</p>
               <p>Beſides the three Tunicles of which we have ſpoken, we remark in the ſubſtance of the ſmall Inteſtines, a heap of little Glandules, which ſend their Excretory Veſſels into the Cavity of the Inteſtines, and Diſtill there a clear and tranſparent
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:51501:66"/> Liquor. We ſhall tell its uſe when we ſpeak of the changes which the Chyle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives in paſſing into the Inteſtines.</p>
               <p>Moreover the Chyle is not very Liquid when it comes out of the Stomach. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles ſomewhat the Paſte which is made by the Boiling of Meal with Water. It is even like to it of a grayiſh colour, and has much ot Viſcoſity. But it does not continue long in that ſtate. It has no ſooner paſt the <hi>Duodenum,</hi> but a yellow and extremely bitter Liquor, which they call the Bile, comes to mingle with it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="discourse">
               <head>The twelfth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Bile <hi>and of the</hi> Liver.</head>
               <p>WHen we enquire by Chymiſtry what are the Elements of the Bile, we find that it is compoſed of much of fixt <hi>Alcalie,</hi> a little <hi>Volatile,</hi> a little of <hi>Sulphur,</hi> yet leſs of <hi>Earth,</hi> and much of <hi>Phlegme.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:51501:66"/>
               <p>From whence we may conclude, that the <hi>Bile</hi> mingling its ſelf with the Chyle, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives in its <hi>Alcalies</hi> both fixt and <hi>Volatile,</hi> a part of the <hi>Acids,</hi> which hold its Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurs united together, and thereby keep up the Viſcoſity which it has in the Duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denum. So that the Sulphurs of the Chyle are after this more at liberty, and more ſeparated one from another. Wherefore they receive amongſt their parts, the Phlegme of the Bile, which dilate the whole Maſſe and give it a greater fluidity.</p>
               <p>The Bile is diſcharged into the Cavity of the Guts, at the end of the <hi>Duodenum</hi> by a ſmall Hole, round about which is obſerved a ſmall Spongious edge. If you put a Probe into this ſmall Hole, it paſſes into a Membranous Conduit, which reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the Liver. This Conduit is always full of Bile. It is therefore called <hi>Canalis Cholidochus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Inſertion of this Veſſel into the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines is ſingular enough. At firſt it creeps above the hinder part of the Duodenum, and then peirces its outer Coat. Afterwards
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:51501:67"/> it peirces its middle Tunicle after having deſcended for ſome ſpace between that and the outer Coat. And in fine, after having made ſome way between the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle. Tunicle and the inner, it pierces the inner at the place where we have obſerved the little Hole through which the Bile flows into the Inteſtines.</p>
               <p>The Obliquity of this Inſertion ſerves to make the Bile run into the Inteſtines. And the ſpongious edge which environs the little Hole hinders the Bile from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from the Inteſtines into the <hi>Ductus Cholidochus.</hi> For the ſpongious edge is a ſmall Sphincter which keeps the little Hole ſhut, when the Bile does not keep it open by flowing into the <hi>Guts.</hi> And the Periſtaltick motion of the Inteſtines paſſing towards the little Hole, ſerves ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that part of the Ductus Cholidochus which creeps amongſt the Membranes of the Duodenum; and thereby obliges all the Bile that is in this part of the Ductus Cholidochus to run into the Cavity of the <hi>Guts.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:51501:67"/>
               <p>After having conſidered all this exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I follow the Ductus Cholidochus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the liver, and I perceive that it is forked there, and that one of its branches goes to a Bladder ſituated beſides the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cave part of the Liver, whileſt the other goes to the Liver. They call the branch which goes to the Bladder <hi>Ductus Cyſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> and that which goes to the Liver <hi>Ductus Hepaticus,</hi> and the Trunck which ariſes from the joyning of both theſe which is inſerted into the end of the Duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denum, <hi>Ductus Communis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hepatick. Conduit enters into the Liver accompanied with two Arteries, two Nerves and the <hi>Vena Porta</hi> All theſe Veſſels are ſhut up in a Membranous ſheath, which they call, <hi>Gliſſon's Capſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</hi> As ſoon as they enter into the Liver, they are divided into many branches, and theſe branches into others, and thus they continue to divide till they be ſpread through all the ſubſtance of the Liver.</p>
               <p>It is here to be remarked that all theſe Veſſels continue ſtill to be ſhut up in <hi>Gliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:51501:68"/> 
                  <hi>Capſula.</hi> It accompanies them thro' all, and follows all their ramifications. So that wherever there is a branch of an Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, there is there alſo a branch of the <hi>Vena Porta,</hi> and one of the Ductus Cholido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus, and the whole is ſhut up in a branch of the Capſula. As for the Nerves they follow alſo the ramification of the other Veſſels for ſome ſpace, and in fine they form a ſmall net, which enfolds the <hi>Arterys</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this by the way we may conclude that the <hi>Vena Porta</hi> does not beat in the Liver, as ſome Authors have imagined; but that the beating of the Capſula pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the beating of the Arteries which are ſhut up in it.</p>
               <p>All theſe Veſſels enter into ſmall Lobes, the Aſſemblage whereof makes up the Liver. Each Lobe is ſhut up in a very deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Membrane which divides it from all the reſt. Nevertheleſs it ceaſes not to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to them by ſmall Tendinous Fibres. The Membrane which enfolds each Lobe degenerates into a part of the Capſula, enfolding all the Veſſels which enter into
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:51501:68"/> the Lobe. So that Gliſſon's Capſula is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the continuation and re-union of all the Membranes which encompaſſe the ſmall Lobes of the Liver.</p>
               <p>All theſe Lobes are made up of little Vaſcular Glandules, which touch one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Each Glandule receives a branch of an Artery and of the <hi>Vena Porta,</hi> and there goes from it a branch of the Ductus Cholidochus, which is nothing but a continuation of the Veſſel of the Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule. They are faſtned to theſe ſmall Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels as Raiſins to the Trunk of the Grape. There goes alſo from each Glandule a branch of the Hepatick Vein, which being united make up a conſiderable Trunk, which goes from the Liver at its convex part, and enters into the aſcending <hi>Vena Cava.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Vena Porta</hi> and the Arteries bring the Blood to the Glandules of the ſmall Lobes, the branches of the Hepatick Vein carry it away again into the <hi>Vena Cava,</hi> and the Ductus Cholidochus tranſports into the end of the Duodenum the Bile,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:51501:69"/> which the Glandules of the ſmall Lobes have ſeparated from the Blood.</p>
               <p>This is what we have diſcovered in following the Ramifications of the Hepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Conduit. Let us now trace the <hi>Ductus Cyſticus.</hi> I remark firſt that it is ſtraitned by a ſmall Fibrous Ring at its Inſertion into the Veſicle of the Bile. So that this Fibrous Ring performs the office of a ſmall Sphincter, which ſhuts the entry of the Veſicle, and hinders the Bile which uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fills it, from getting out, unleſs it be forced. Afterwards I conſider the <hi>Veſicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Fellis.</hi> It has the figure of a ſmall Pear, and it receives Arteries from the Caeliack, which are called the <hi>Cystick Arteries.</hi> It is made up of two Tunicles, between which there are a prodigious number of ſmall Veſicular Glandules, which receive branches from the Cyſtick Arteries. The Excretory Veſſels of theſe little Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules do peirce its inner Coat, and make within its Cavity a ſmall Down, from whence there flows a very clear and Tranſparent Bile in form of a Dew. This
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:51501:69"/> Bile differs from that which flows from the Hepatick Conduit, in this, that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is of a deeper colour and abounds more in a fixt Alcalie, whereas this is more fluid, and has more of a Volatile Alcalie than the other.</p>
               <p>All the Bile which is found in the Veſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula Fellis, does not come only from the Veſicular Glandules ſituated between its Tunicles; but a great part of it comes from the Lobes of the Liver which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Veſicle. They diſcharge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into its Cavity by two or three <hi>Ductus Cholidoci,</hi> which are inſerted into that part of it that adheres to the Liver. Amongſt the reſt there is one conſiderable enough which peirces the Tunicles of the Veſicula Fellis near the Fibrous Ring. The mouth of this Veſſel is encompaſſed with a ſmall Spongious border, which ſerves it for a Sphincter.</p>
               <p>There goes a great number of Lympha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Veſſels, both from the concave part of the Liver, and from the Veſicle, which enter into the Reſervatory that is
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:51501:70"/> placed above the Vertebrae of the Loins.</p>
               <p>In fine, the Liver has three Ligaments which keep it in its ſituation. The firſt keeps it ſtrongly faſtned to the Diaphrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and it peirces into the ſubſtance of the Liver, even to Gliſſon's Capſula. The ſecond is of a good length, it is faſtned to the Liver near the Bladder of the Gall, and it goes to the Navel. The third is ſlack, but ſtrong and large. It derives its Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine from the Membrane which encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes the whole Liver, and which is a production of the Peritonaeum, and it goes from thence to the Xiphoid Cartilage.</p>
               <p>Its upper part is Convex, and its under Concave, is divided into three or four great Lobes, and by its under part it em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces a part of the Stomach So that when the Stomach is full of Meat, the Bladder of the Gall being then preſt, the Bile goes out by the Cyſtick <hi>Channel,</hi> and runs in abundance into the <hi>Duodenum,</hi> to diſſolve the Chyle according as it comes from the Stomach.</p>
               <p>From all this therefore, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:51501:70"/> that the uſe of the Liver is to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Bile from the Blood, to perfect the Chyle in the Inteſtines, by diſſolving its Sulphurs by its <hi>Alcalies,</hi> and by diluting it with its Phlegme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="discourse">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Thirteenth Diſcourſe.</hi> Of the Changes which the <hi>Chyle</hi> receives in the <hi>Inteſtines.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEſides the <hi>Bile</hi> which is diſcharged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Duodenum; there is alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Liquor Clear and Tranſparent as Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which advances thither, and which they call the <hi>Pancreatick Juyce.</hi> This Pancreatick Juyce is ſomewhat of the ſame nature with the Lympha, that is, that it is compoſed of Sulphurs, Phlegms and Volatile Alcalies.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as it falls into the Inteſtins, it mingles with the Chyle. If it rencounters any <hi>Acids</hi> in the Chyle, which keep its Sulphurs united, its Volatile Alcalie
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:51501:71"/> charges its ſelf with them, which frees the Sulphurs from the other Principles. The Sulphurs which are in the Pancreatick Juyce, thruſt themſelves amongſt the parts of the Chyle. They moderate the Fermentation of the Alcalies with the Acids, and hinder it from being done with too much Violence, which would occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion much diſorder. And the Phlegme make way to the Alcalies and Sulphurs, and they mingle more exactly with all the parts of the Chyle.</p>
               <p>From all this it follows clearly enough that the Pancreatick Juyce perfects the Chyle and renders it more Liquid. In men the Pancreatick Juyce and the Bile do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Inteſtine at the ſame Hole. And in the moſt part of other Animals the Pancreatick Conduit is inſerted into the Jejunum two Inches below the Inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Ductus Cholidochus.</hi> We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark in this Inſertion of the Pancreatick Conduit almoſt the ſame circumſtances which have been obſerved in the Inſertion of the <hi>Ductus Cholidochus.</hi> About the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:51501:71"/> little Hole from whence the Pancreatick Juyce flows into the Cavity of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines, there is a little Fibrous edge, which ſerves it for a Sphincter, and hinders any thing from paſſing from the Inteſtines into the Pancreatick Conduit.</p>
               <p>This Conduit is made of many others, which ſpread, through a Glandulous Body, which they call the <hi>Pancreas.</hi> The Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules which compoſe it, are Vaſcular of a reaſonable bigneſs. There goes from each a ſmall Conduit which is Inoſculated into the Pancreatick Conduit, and ſheds into its Cavity the Liquor which the Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule has ſeparated from the Blood.</p>
               <p>The whole Pancreas is covered with one Tunicle. It receives Arteries from the Caeliack, it ſends Veins to the Sple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick, and ſome Ramifications of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercoſtal come thither, and ſpread through all its Body.</p>
               <p>It is ſo needfull for the conſervation of of the Animal, that the Chyle ſhould be freed of its Acids, that the Author of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has plac'd many heaps of Veſicular
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:51501:72"/> Glandules between the Tunicles of the ſmall Inteſtines. They diſtill into theſe places a Liquor like unto the pancreatick Juyce. By its mixture with the Chyle is finiſheth what the Bile and the pancreatick Juyce had ſo well begun.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſmall heaps of Glandules are of different bigneſſes. There are of them which contain more than two hundred Glandules, and there are of them again which have not thirty. Sometimes there are four of them, ſometimes five, and ſometimes ſix. Sometimes there are two of them in the Jejunum, ſometimes three, and ſometimes but one: we find alwayes two or three ſuch heaps in the Ilium.</p>
               <p>All the parts of the Chyle are not fit to Paſs into the ſmall Veſſels which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Lacteal Veins. Some of them too groſs, and theſe are they which are called the groſs Excrements. The Chyle abounds in parts fit to paſs into the Lacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Veins, after that it has been prepared by the Bile and the pancreatick Juyce. It is for this that its maſſe doth diminiſh
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:51501:72"/> ſo much in the Jejune Inteſtines for that its more ſubtile parts get out and paſs into the Lacteal Veins. So it is obſerved that there are more Lacteal Veins of the Jejunum, than of all the other Inteſtines. At the end of the Jejunum ſome Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are found mingled with many Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous parts. The Glandulous juyce min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles with them and diſſolves the Sulphurs from the Chylous parts which are there. What has thus been prepared paſſes like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe into the Lacteal Veins. Theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements do afterwards paſs into the Ilium, where in divers places they receive again of the Glandulous Juyce, which doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame effect as formerly. In fine, after they are entirely freed of their Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous parts, they paſs into the greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines. They are then compoſed of parts which the Ferment of the Stomach could not diſſolve, and of ſalts which are formed by the union of Alcalies, of the Bile, of the pancreatick Juyce, and of the Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Juyce with the Acids, which were engaged amongſt the parts of the Chyle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="discourse">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:51501:73"/>
               <head>The fourteenth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Meſentery, <hi>the</hi> Lacteal Veins, Pecquets Reſervatory, <hi>and the</hi> Thora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cick Conduit.</head>
               <p>THe Inteſtines adhere to the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of a Membranous Ruffe, which they call the <hi>Meſentery.</hi> The mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of it is ſo ſtrongly faſtned to the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebraes of the Loins, that it cannot be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from them, unleſs you tear a part of it, or cut it. It is compoſed of two Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes, of which the upper is a continuation of the Peritonaeum, and the inferiour a Texture of Tendinous Fibres which come from the Vertebraes of the Loins.</p>
               <p>The Meſenterick Arterie ſpreads many branches amongſt the Membranes of the Meſentery, one part of which goes to the Inteſtines, and the other is ſpread amongſt the Fibres of the Membranes which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it. The Veins which come from
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:51501:73"/> the Inteſtines are likewiſe ſpread between the Membranes of the Meſentery, and many ſmall Veins which come from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their Fibres, go thither. They are called the <hi>Meſaraick Veins.</hi> They go to the <hi>Vena Porta.</hi> Many Nerves which ariſe from the Vertebraes of the Loins, and from the Intercoſtal, are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven one with another upon the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentery, that they form a Plexus which is called the <hi>Meſenterick Plexus.</hi> Many Nervous Fibres go from it, which are ſpread amongſt the Fibres of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes of the Meſentery, and a part of which paſſes even to the Inteſtines.</p>
               <p>The middle between the Membranes of the Meſentery is repleniſht with Far. It appears cheifly about the Meſaraick Veins. In the midſt of it we find a large Glandule, and ſometimes two, three or four. In Oxen and ſome other Animals there are many more, and they are plac'd towards the ſmall Inteſtines. The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſtructure of theſe Glandules does admirably ſerve to explain their uſes.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:51501:74"/> They are a heap of angular Veſicles. There is a communication between their Cavites. This is found by blowing into them after you have thruſt out all that fills them. The Air paſſes from one Veſicle to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and makes them appear ſuch as we have deſcribed them.</p>
               <p>In fine, we diſcover between the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes of the Meſentery certain ſmall Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which come from the Inteſtines and paſs into the Glandules of which we have ſpoken.</p>
               <p>Theſe Veſſels are ordinarly full of Lympha, and ſometimes we find them full of Liquor like to Milk. which is the reaſon why they call them the Lacteal Veins.</p>
               <p>This Milk is nothing but the pure Chyle, which has paſt from the Cavity of the ſmall Inteſtines into that of the Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teal Veins. There are four Experiments which confirm us in this Opinion. The firſt is, that the Milk which runs into the Lacteal Veins comes from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines, this truth appears to the Eye,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:51501:74"/> when the Lacteal Veins are preſt with the Fingers. They empty themſelves of the Milk, and we ſee it come afterwards from the ſide of the Inteſtines to fill the Vein which has been emptied. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is, that Milk is not to be found in the Lacteal Veins but ſome Hours after the Animal has eaten. The third is, that we find the Jejunum almoſt alwayes empty, becauſe of the great number of Lacteal Veins which goe from it.</p>
               <p>Moreover the Lacteal Veins have many Valves plac'd very near one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They are ſo diſpoſed that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Chyle to run eaſily into the Lacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Veins in going from the Inteſtines to the Glandules of the Meſentery, but they hinder its return. They go from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines in great number, and they are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſculated many of them together accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they advance. By this means they make up ſome greater Veſſels which empty the Chyle that they carry, into the Veſicles of the Glandules of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentery.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:51501:75"/>
               <p>The Chyle goes into the Veſicles of theſe Glandules, to receive there Animal Spirits, which come thither in abundance by many Nerves which proceed from the Meſenterick Plexus. Theſe Spirits render the Chyle more ſubtile and fluid by their Volatile Alcalie, and if there be any aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in it, they correct it, by receiving it into their Alcalies and changing it into Salt.</p>
               <p>After that the Chyle has paſt through the Veſicles of the Meſaraick Glandules, it diſcharges its ſelf into two or three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits which ariſe from under them. They end afterwards in a Membranous bag ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated above the Vertebras of the Loins, they call it the <hi>Reſervatory</hi> of the Chyle. The Reſervatory is the ſame thing with the Ciſtern of the Lympha, of which we have ſpoken before. In this place the Chyle is mingled with much Lympha, with which the Reſervatory is alwayes full. It dilates it, and renders it more Liquid, that it may run the more eaſily.</p>
               <p>In fine, there goes from the Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:51501:75"/> of the Chyle, a Conduit, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Thoracick Conduit,</hi> for that it goes alongſt the Vertebraes of the Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax. Sometimes this Conduit is forked, and its branches unite again, ſometimes it is altogether ſimple.</p>
               <p>The Thoracick Conduit is inſerted into the Subclavian Vein, above its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion there is a Valve, which like a ſmall Vault covers it. So that the Blood which runs through the Subclavian Vein, runs by without hindring the entry of the Chyle.</p>
               <p>When we blow in the Thoracick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit, we perceive many Valves in its Cavity. They are plac'd at very ſmall diſtances from one another, and are ſo diſpoſed that they permit the Chyle eaſily to run towards the Subclavian Vein, but they hinder it from deſcending into Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets Reſervatory.</p>
               <p>From whence we may conclude that the Chyle runs from its Reſervatory by the Thoracick Conduit into the left Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clavian Vein. There it mingles with the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:51501:76"/> Blood. Whoſe courſe it follows and goes into the <hi>Vena Cava,</hi> which carries it into the right Auricle of the Heart. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricle diſcharges it into the right Ventricle. And whereas the Chyle makes then a part of the Blood, it follows its courſe, and circulats with it through all the Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="discourse">
               <head>The fifteenth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen the Chyle is once entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Subclavian Vein, it ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les its ſelf with the Blood, and follows its courſe. We muſt therefore follow the Blood, if we could know what becomes of the Chyle.</p>
               <p>The circulation of the Blood ſhews us that it runs from the Subclavian Vein into the <hi>Vena Cava,</hi> and from the <hi>Vena Cava</hi> it paſſes into a bag adhering to the right ſide of the Heart. This little bag they call the <hi>right Auricle of the Heart.</hi> When this
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:51501:76"/> Auricle is full of Blood it contracts its ſelf, and in contracting its ſelf ſheds it into a Cavity which we find in the Body of the Heart on its right ſide. This Cavity is called the <hi>right Ventricle of the Heart.</hi> As ſoon as the Ventricle is full of Blood, it contracts its ſelf, and empties its ſelf by this contraction.</p>
               <p>It is here to be remarked, that at the opening of the right Auricle into the right Ventricle of the Heart, there are certain ſmall Skins, which they call Valves. They are three in number, almoſt of a trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Figure, whoſe ſides are notched. Their Baſe adheres to the opening of the Auricle, and their point is plac'd within the Ventricle. Their point is upheld only by ſmall Tendinous Fibres, ſtrong and of a good Length, which without being ſtretch'd are ſtrongly faſtned to ſmall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous pillars, plac'd upon the concave ſurface of the Ventricle This diſpoſition ſhews to the Eye that theſe Valves are ſo many ſmall doors, which the Blood opens of its ſelf, when it runs from the Auricle
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:51501:77"/> into the Ventricle, and which it ſhuts after it is entered there. Indeed as ſoon as the Ventricle is full of Blood it contracts its ſelf, and the Blood is preſt equally on all ſides by this contraction. For this cauſe it gets under theſe Valves, lifts up their point towards the opening of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricle, which is thereby ſo exactly ſhut, that no drop of Blood can paſs that way. So the Blood ſhuts up to its ſelf this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and cannot get out the way by which it has entered. Nevertheleſs it does not ſtay in the right Ventricle of the Heart, it goes out by another door, to which the beginning of an Artery is ſtrongly faſtned. This Artery is divided into many branches, which diſtribute themſelves into the Lobes of the Lungs. At its paſſing from the right Ventricle it has in its Cavity three Valves made like Creſcents, and ranked each at the ſide of the other. Their Convexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty adheres to the Artery and turns to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Ventricle, and their Concavity is diſengag'd and turned towards the Artery. This ſituation ſhews us that
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:51501:77"/> they do not oppoſe the motion of the Blood when it comes from the Ventricle to the Artery, but by riſing up they ſtop its courſe if it preſſe from the Artery into the Ventricle.</p>
               <p>After that the Blood has paſt from the right Ventricle into the Lungs by the Pulmonary Artery, it returns from them by a Vein, which is called the <hi>Pulmonary Vein.</hi> This Pulmonary Vein diſcharges its ſelf into a little bag, faſtned to the left ſide of the Heart, which is called the <hi>left Auricle.</hi> As ſoon as this Auricle is full, it contracts its ſelf, thruſts by its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction the Blood into a Cavity in the ſubſtance of the Heart, plac'd on its left ſide which is called the <hi>left Ventricle</hi> As ſoon as this Cavity is full of Blood it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts its ſelf, and by this contraction throws out all the Blood which it contains.</p>
               <p>That we may learn where the Blood goes when it paſſes from the left Ventricle of the Heart, we are to take notice that at the opening of the left Auricle there are Valves ſituated, after the ſame manner
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:51501:78"/> as at the opening of the right Ventricle. Their uſe alſo is the ſame. They permit indeed the Blood to run from the Auricle into the Ventricle, but they hinder it from coming out of the Ventricle into the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricle when the Heart contracts its ſelf. The Blood therefore takes another way. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it gets out of the left Ventricle by another paſſage, which makes the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the great Artery, which they call the <hi>Aorta.</hi> We find in the Cavity of this Artery next to the Heart, three Valves made Creſcent wayes, diſpoſed after the ſame manner as thoſe of the Pulmonary Artery. They permit the Blood to get out of the left Ventricle and to run into the Aorta, but they hinder the Blood from flowing back from the Aorta into the left Ventricle.</p>
               <p>There is yet an important remark to be made upon the motion of the Auricles and Ventricles of the Heart. It is, that the two Auricles do contract and dilate themſelves at the ſame time, and the two Ventricles in like manner. With this Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:51501:78"/> that at the time the Auricles contract themſelves, the Ventricles are dilated, and when the Ventricles contract themſelves, the Auricles are dilated in courſe. Which makes us conjecture, that the Heart is a Muſcle, whoſe Auricles may well be reputed the Antagoniſt Muſcles.</p>
               <p>Before we enquire if this conjecture be a truth, it will not be impertinent to obſerve, that ſince the Auricles contract themſelves at the ſame time, they do alſo at the ſame time ſhed the Blood into the Ventricles of the Heart. By the ſame reaſon the Ventricles of the Heart do at one time preſs the Blood into the Pulmonary Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and into the Aorta.</p>
               <p>When we conſider the Heart narrowly, we perceive that it is compoſed of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Fibres, which have all of them communication with a Membrane made of Tendinous Fibres. This Membrane is plac'd at the Baſe of the Heart, and keeps the Auricles fixt to it. Which makes us judge that the Heart is a Muſcle.</p>
               <p>In the Heart we obſerve three orders of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:51501:79"/> Fibres, the firſt is, of thoſe which go in a ſtraight line from the Baſis of the Heart juſt to its point; and they lye in a ſmall number over the right Ventricle. The ſecond is of thoſe which go from the Baſe, and after they have extended themſelves to the middle of the Heart, aſcend again and return to the Baſe from whence they came. The third is of thoſe which goe from the Baſe and come to the point, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing about the Heart a ſpiral Line. There they re-enter within the Heart, and re-aſcend ſpirally towards the Baſe. Some of them end in the Ventricles, where they make a Texture of their Tendinous Fibres, which covers them on all ſides. Some of thoſe alſo which come into the Ventricles make thoſe little Eminencies which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pillars.</hi> From the point of theſe Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars go many Tendinous Strings, which are joyned to the Teeth of the Valves that are plac'd in the opening of the Auricles.</p>
               <p>All theſe Orders of Fibres do ſerve by the ſhortning of themſelves to contract the Ventricles of the Heart. The ſtraight Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:51501:79"/> ſhorten it, the circular ones ſtraiten it, and the ſpiral wring it. The Heart can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be thus ſhortned, ſtraitned and wreath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the Ventricles muſt needs be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted. From whence we muſt conclude, that the Heart is a Muſcle, whoſe action conſiſts in ſtraitning the Cavities which are amongſt its Fibres.</p>
               <p>As for the Auricles, they are alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of Carneous Fibres, of which ſome of them are interwoven with others. They are extended for the moſt part to the length, and thoſe of them which are interwoven ſeem to croſs them to become Circular. The ſhortning of the firſt does diminiſh the length of the Auricles, and the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the other diminiſheth their breadth. Which ſhews us that the Auricles are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Cavernous Muſcles, whoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſts in the contraction of their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</p>
               <p>There is a communication between the Fibres of the Heart and thoſe of the Auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, by the interpoſal of the Tendinous Fibres, which are gathered altogether pure
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:51501:80"/> at the Baſe of the Heart. We may look upon them as a Tendon common to the Heart and the Auricles. The animal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits therefore which the Nerves diſtil into this Tendon, do eaſily paſs from the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of the Heart into the Fibres of the Auricles, and from the Fibres of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles into thoſe of the Heart.</p>
               <p>If we would yet form to our ſelves an Idaea of the Heart as clear and diſtinct as may be, we may conſider it as a Muſcle with three Bellies. Each Auricle makes one, and the Body of the Heart makes the third, and the Membrane which is at the Baſe of the Heart where the Fibres of the Heart and of the Auricles do meet, would be the common Tendon.</p>
               <p>The Heart receives Arteries from the Aorta, it ſends Veins to the Cava; it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives Nerves from the plexus Cardiacus and the <hi>Par Vagum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In fine, the Heart is ſhut up in a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branous Bag which is called the <hi>Pericar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</hi> The Pericardium is ſtrong and it is formed of a Texture of the Tendinous
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:51501:80"/> Fibres of the Heart, of ſome Veins, ſome Arteries and ſome Nerves. It contains always a little Seroſity, which the ſmall Glandules that are plac'd amongſt the Fat of the Baſe of the Heart do diſtill into it.</p>
               <p>From what has been ſaid, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that when the Auricles are full of Blood, the Ventricles of the Heart are empty. And for that the Auricles, how ſoon they are full of Blood, do contract themſelves; the Blood which they preſs into the Ventricles of the Heart, being aided by the ſpring of their Fibres, does dilate them, and conſtrains the animal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to get out of them, and to run into the Auricles to accompliſh their contraction. But as ſoon as the Auricles are contracted, the Blood which advances on all ſides, joynn'd with the force of the ſpring of their Fibres, reſtores them to their former ſtate. And the Spirits paſſing in that moment from the Auricles to the Heart, ſhut it up, and cauſe its contraction. It is for this Reaſon that the Auricles empty themſelves when the Ventricles of the Heart are filled,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:51501:81"/> and that the Auricles fill themſelves when the Ventricles are emptied.</p>
               <p>The heart by its Contraction throws the Blood from its Ventricles into the Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. But for that the Artery become ſtill narrower, the Blood cannot be thrown out impetuouſly without ſwelling them When they are thus blown up, they reſtore them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their former ſtate by the ſpring of their Fibres, and by this mean make a part of the Blood which they have received run into the Veins of the Heart. And ſince the Heart throws out the Blood into the Arteries by ſeveral ſtrokes, the Arteries muſt needs be blown up and fall again by ſeveral turns. It is this motion of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries which they call the <hi>Pulſe,</hi> concerning which it is to be remarked that the dilata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Arteries accompanies the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of the Heart, and the contraction of the Arteries accompanies its dilatation.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who are ſatisfied with what they conceive clearly, will be contented to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe to the Heart the office of preſſing the Blood into the Arteries, and of being the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:51501:81"/> principal Inſtrument of its Circulation. They may leave to thoſe who believe that the Heart is the Organ of ſanguification, the ſatisfaction they have to be pleaſed with a conjecture ill founded, as ſhall be made appear afterwards.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="discourse">
               <head>The Sixteenth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the</hi> Lungs.</head>
               <p>WE have ſaid in the preceeding Chapter, that when the Blood goes from the right Ventricle of the Heart it paſſes into the Pulmonary Artery. This Artery is divided into many great branches which enter into the Body of the Lungs, and theſe branches are again divided into others, and theſe into others, till at laſt the ſmalleſt of them are loſt into the ſubſtance of the Lungs.</p>
               <p>The Pulmonary Artery is not ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in the Lungs. It is every where ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the Pulmonary Vein, a branch of a Nerve which comes from the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:51501:82"/> 
                  <hi>Par Vagum,</hi> a ſmall Artery which goes from the <hi>Aorta,</hi> and which they call the <hi>Bronchial Artery,</hi> with a ſmall Vein which is paſſing into the <hi>Vena Cava,</hi> and which they call the <hi>Bronchial Vein;</hi> and a certain Cartilaginous Conduit, which they name the <hi>Bronchiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Bronchiae are nothing but the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mifications of a great Cartilaginous Pipe, which extends its ſelf from the bottom of the Mouth, even to the Lungs. It lyeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Oeſophagus, and is plac'd in the fore part of the Neck. They call it the <hi>Arteria Trachaea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is at the top of the <hi>Arteria Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaea</hi> a horny part, which they name the <hi>Larinx.</hi> It is made up of five Cartilages. That which takes up its forepart, makes that Eminence which in men they call <hi>Adams Bit.</hi> Its Figure is almoſt like unto that of that Buckler which amongſt the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines is called <hi>Scutum</hi> For this reaſon they name it the Scutiform Cartilage. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is called the <hi>Annular.</hi> It is made like the Ring which the Turks make uſe of for
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:51501:82"/> drawing the Bow. It is ſtrait before and large behind. It embraces the whole La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinx, and is faſtned into the Scutiform. The third and fourth are called the <hi>Aritenoides.</hi> They are the productions of the Annular, placed on its hinder part, and ſeparated from one another by a ſmall ſlit. They make that part of the Larinx which they call the <hi>Glottis.</hi> The fifth is a Cartilage faſtned above the upper part of the Scuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Cartilage. They call it the <hi>Epiglot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> Its Figure is Triangular, and its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſofter than that of the others. Its Baſe adheres to the Scutiform Cartilage, and the reſt of its Body is diſengag'd from any other part. It is uſually lifted up. This is that Cartilage which the Aliments put down in paſſing from the Mouth, into the Oeſophagus. When it is down it ſhuts the entry of the Trachaeal Artery, and thereby hinders the Aliments from going into it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Larinx</hi> is reckoned to have thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Muſcles. There are four of them, which are common to it with other parts, and nine which do properly appertain to
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:51501:83"/> it. The firſt pair of the common ones are nam'd the <hi>Sternothyoidians.</hi> They ariſe from the top of the <hi>Sternum,</hi> lye above the Trachaeal Artery, and are faſtned to the inferiour part of the Scutiform Carti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage. When their Fibres are contracted they draw the Scutiform downwards. The ſecond pair is made of the <hi>Hyothyroidians.</hi> They ariſe from the Baſe of the os Hyoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and are faſtned to the Baſe of the Scuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. They ſerve by the contraction of their Fibres to lift up the Larinx.</p>
               <p>The firſt pair of Muſcles proper to the Larinx is made of the anteriour <hi>Cricothy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roidians.</hi> They derive their origin from the forepart of the annular Cartilage, and they end at the lower part of the ſame Carti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage. By their action they dilate it. The ſecond is made of the Poſteriour <hi>Crico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyroidians.</hi> They ariſe from the top of the annular at its hinder part and come to the ſides of the Scutiform at its upper part. When they act they ſtraiten the Scutiform. The third is made of the <hi>Cricoavitheno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idians.</hi> They derive their origine from
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:51501:83"/> the inner, and ſide part of the annular, and are inſerted into the under part and the ſides of the Arithenoides. By their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction they dilate the <hi>Glottis.</hi> The fourth is made of the <hi>Thyroarithenoidians,</hi> They come from within, and from the middle of the Scutiform, and are termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated in the ſides of the Arithenoides, By their action they ſhut the Larinx. The ninth Muſcle is called the <hi>Arithenoidian.</hi> It ariſeth from the place where the annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar is joyn'd with the Arithenoides which it ſtraitens when it acts.</p>
               <p>The Larinx covers the top of the <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheal Artery,</hi> whoſe frame is ſingular en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Firſt we find it covered with a very delicate Membrane whoſe Fibres are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly interwoven Then under this Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane there are Cartilaginous rings. Theſe rings are entirely Cartilaginous except on their Back-ſide, where they are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branous. It is by this place they touch the Oeſophagus. They are not Carti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laginous that they may yeild to the Oeſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phagus, when any great and hard morſel paſſes alongſt its Cavity.</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:51501:84"/>
               <p>Theſe Cartilaginous Rings are not all of the ſame groſſneſs. That which up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds the Larinx is greater and larger than that which follows, and this is larger than the next, and ſo forward. So that the more they approach the Lungs their breadth diminiſheth. They are all united together by carneous Ligaments, and it is remarked that they are all equally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant the one from the other.</p>
               <p>When they enter into the Body of the Lungs they are nam'd the <hi>Bronchiae.</hi> There they ceaſe to be Membranous on their back-part and become entirely Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilaginous. And wheras in the Tracheal Artery its Rings are equally diſtant from one another, in the Bronchiae, they are joyned in ſuch a manner as that a part of the Inferiour Ring enters into the Cavity of its Superiour.</p>
               <p>The Cartilaginous Rings of the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheal Artery, and of the Bronchiae, do cover a Tunicle compoſed of three principal Parts. How ſoon you raiſe up one of the Cartilaginous Rings you find a Muſculous
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:51501:84"/> Tunicle. Its Fibres are diſpoſed as the Fibres of the middle Tunicle of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines. The Longitudinals appear firſt and afterwards we ſee the Circulars. They are plac'd preciſely under the Longitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals. This Carneous Tunicle covers another Tunicle which is nothing but an aſſemblage of ſmall Glandules, even as the Carneous Tunicle of the Stomach does immediately cover the Glandulous. And in fine, under this Glandulous Tunicle there is another, which is nothing but a Texture of Tendinous Fibres which come from the Carneous Tunicle; There are ſome Filaments of Nerves, and ſome ſmall Arteries and Veins.</p>
               <p>In the Lungs the Tracheal Artery is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into many branches. Theſe branches are again divided into many branches, and theſe again into many others, and ſo on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward till the laſt end into an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſmall Veſicles. Theſe Veſicles do compoſe the ſubſtance of the Lungs.</p>
               <p>The Veſicles which are gathered about one and of the Bronchiae are all encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:51501:85"/> with one Membrane. This Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane is nothing but the continuation of the outer Tunicle which covers the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheal Artery and the Bronchiae. It is theſe parcels of the Lungs thus diſtinguiſh from one another by the ſmall Membranes which enfold them, that they call the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buls of the Lungs.</p>
               <p>Theſe Lobuls are all faſtned to large Trunks of the Bronchiae as grapes to the ſtalk of the Cluſter. It is from theſe Trunks of the Bronchiae that the ſmall branch proceeds whoſe Capillary branches end in their Veſicles. The Lobules are likewiſe joyn'd together, by ſmall Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous Filaments, which keep their Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles contiguous. Therefore to diſcern them well they muſt be ſeparated with the point of a Pen knife.</p>
               <p>The Bronchiae are every where accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with Arteries and Viens. So we need only trace the Bronchiae to diſcern the courſe of theſe Veſſels. By this mean we find that their Extremities are ſpread into the Coats of the Veſicles, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the ſubſtance of the Lungs.</p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:51501:85"/>
               <p>And for that the Bronchiae are alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a Nerve which follows all their Ramifications, and is loſt into the Veſicles of the Lungs; and in that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Tunicle of the Bronchiae is compoſed of Tendinous Fibres, in all appearance the Veſicles of the Lungs are made of nothing but a Texture of Tendinous Fibres, Fila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Nerves, ſome Arteries and ſome Veins.</p>
               <p>When we blow into the Trachaeal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie the whole maſs of the Lungs ſwells and all the Veſicles are fill'd with Air. From whence I conclude that there is a communication between the Bronchiae and the Veſicles. And ſince we ſee that the Tracheal Artery communicates with the outward Air by the Mouth and the Noſtrils, we may with reaſon conclude that all this apparatus of the Tracheal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie and the Bronchiae has been made for conveying of the External Air into the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicles of the Lungs.</p>
               <p>But becauſe we find that the Longitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal and Circular Fibres of the Tracheal
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:51501:86"/> Arterie and the Bronchiae, cannot by their action but ſhorten the Bronchiae and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Cavity more narrow, we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidged to think that the External Air is thruſt out of the Veſicles of the Lungs. But ſince they are not made but for receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, it appears that it re-enters as ſoon as it has gone out, and that it gets out as ſoon as it has re-entred, and that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues thus to go in and get out, ſo long as the Animal is in Life. And it is this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Air and its Egreſs from the Lungs, which they call <hi>Reſpiration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After we have thus examined the Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the Lungs, we have found indeed the force which thruſts out the Air, when it is entred into the Veſicles, but we do not perceive what may be the force which makes it re-enter there. This makes us think that that force which doth preſs the Air into the Lungs, is not to be ſought for, in the Lungs themſelves, but in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part.</p>
               <p>In ſearching what this force may be, I conſider that the Lungs are ſhut up in a
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:51501:86"/> large. Cavity which they call the <hi>Breaſt,</hi> and that the Breaſt is ſo cloſely ſhut up on all ſides, that the Air cannot get into it but by the Tracheal Artery. By this I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that if the Breaſt dilate it ſelf it will preſs the outward Air into the Lungs to fill the place, which the ſides of the Breaſt do abandon, in the time that it enlarges its ſelf. After the ſame manner that the external Air is thruſt into the Cavity of a pair of bellows, according as you raiſe their Boards.</p>
               <p>Indeed we find that the Air enters into the Lungs according as the Breaſt is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, and that it gets out as it is ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But becauſe it may be enlarged for that the Air enters into the Lungs, and it may be diminiſhed for that it gets out, we muſt examine the ſtructure of the Breaſt, that thereby we may find how to determine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="discourse">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:51501:87"/>
               <head>The ſeventeenth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the Breaſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt thing I meet with in examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cavity of the Breaſt, is a very ſlender Membrane which covers it on all ſides, and which the Anatomiſts call the <hi>Pleura.</hi> This Membrane is doubled on the middle of the Breaſt. It extends its ſelf thus from the top of the Breaſt to the lower part of it, it divides it into two parts, of which the one is on the Right, the other on the Left ſide. They call this ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Mediaſtinum</hi> or <hi>Midriffe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Without the <hi>Pleura</hi> are the Ribs. They are inſerted on one ſide into the Vertebraes. They are bended in form of a <hi>Parabola,</hi> and are united by a Cartilaginous knot, to a Bone which covers the fore-part of the Breaſt, and which they call the <hi>Sternum.</hi> The Ribs touch one another towards the Vertebraes. They are ſeparated according as they advance toward the <hi>Sternum.</hi> The
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:51501:87"/> ſpace which they leave between them is all fill'd with Muſcles, which keeps them united to one another. The firſt which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear are eleven in number. They derive their Origine from the top and the bottom of each inferiour Rib, and aſcending ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely from behind to the Fore part, they draw the Superiour Rib to the Inferiour. They are called the Inner Intercoſtal Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
               <p>Beyond the inner Intercoſtals, there are eleven Muſcles, which they call the outer Intercoſtals. They ariſe all from the Inferiour and outer part of each Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Rib, and are obliquely inſerted in the fore-part unto the Superiour and outer part of each inferior Rib. Their Fibres croſs thoſe of the inner Intercoſtals, in form of a Burgundy Croſs.</p>
               <p>Theſe Muſcles cannot ſerve by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of their Fibres, but to approach the Ribs towards one another. But for as much as the Ribs are ſo ſituated that they cannot approach one another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the Breaſt muſt be enlarged, we
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:51501:88"/> conclude that the uſe of the Intercoſta Muſcles is to enlarge the Breaſt, by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ribs upward.</p>
               <p>The External Intercoſtals are covered with many other Muſcles. We obſerve amongſt the reſt one of them which comes from the <hi>Os Sacrum</hi> and the Thorny <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſes</hi> of the Loyns, and is inſerted into the upper Ribs near their Roots. It gives to each one of them a double Tendon. They call it the <hi>Sacro-Lumbar,</hi> when it acts it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves the Ribs from one another by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them downward.</p>
               <p>There is after this another, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives its Origine from the middle of the <hi>Sternum.</hi> It is faſtned to the Cartilages of the true under Ribs, and to the ſecond and third of the baſtard ones. They give it the Name of the <hi>Triangular Muſcle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this appears a great Muſcle large enough, which ariſes from the inner Baſe of the Homoplate, and is joyned to the five true inferiour Ribs, and to the two baſtard inferior Ribs by five Tendons which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the Teeth of a Saw. It is for this
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:51501:88"/> that they Name it the Great Teethed Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. And when it acts, it draws all the Ribs towards the <hi>Homo plate</hi> to which it ſends the Tendons.</p>
               <p>Then when we go back towards the top of the Breaſt, we find a Muſcle which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives its Origine from within the Clavicle near the Acromion, and is faſtned to the firſt Rib near the <hi>Sternum.</hi> Its uſe is to draw the firſt Rib upwards towards the <hi>Clavicle.</hi> They call it the <hi>Subcla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We find alſo another Muſcle which comes from the Thorn of the three Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Vertebraes of the Neck, and the firſt of the Back. It is terminated by digitation into the three or four upper Ribs They call it the upper ſmall Teethed Muſcle. It draws the Ribs into which it is inſerted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards towards the Neck.</p>
               <p>In fine, there is yet one which ariſeth from the three Inferiour Vertebraes of the Back and the firſt of the Loyns It is inſerted into the three or four Inferiour Ribs by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation. It draws outwards the Ribs into
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:51501:89"/> which it is inſerted. They call it the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ſmall Teethed Muſcle.</p>
               <p>The Ribs are ſo diſpoſed that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be moved upwards without enlarging the capacity of the Breaſt. And ſince the four laſt Muſcles of which we have ſpoken do draw the Ribs upwards, we may truly affirm that their uſe is to enlarge the Breaſt, and the uſe of the others to diminiſh it.</p>
               <p>The Breaſt is ſhut up below by a muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous wall, which they call the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragm. This wall is not alwayes bended. This may appear, in that when the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal is dead, it is Convex towards the Breaſt, and concave on the other ſide. So by its Convexity it takes up a part of the capacity of the Breaſt.</p>
               <p>Its figure is almoſt round. We remark in it two eſſential parts, the Carneous and the Tendinous. The Tendinous occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies the middle. It is Tranſparent and woven of Tendinous Fibres and Nervous Filaments. The Carneous part encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth the Tendinous. It extends its ſelf to the <hi>Sternum,</hi> to the Ribs, and to ſome
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:51501:89"/> Vertebra's of the Back, as well as to ſome of thoſe of the Loins. It is ſtrongly faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to all theſe parts Its Fibres go in a ſtraight line from the Tendinous part, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the places of their Inſertion.</p>
               <p>From whence we may eaſily conclude that when the Diaphragm acts the Carne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fibres by their Contraction draw the Tendinous part towards the ſides. So they make the Diaphragm loſe its Convexity. And ſince that thereby it leaves the place which it occupied in the Breaſt, this Cavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is conſiderably enlarged. Which makes us judge that the Diaphragm ſerves by its action to enlarge the Cavity of the Breaſt.</p>
               <p>The Diaphragm is brought down alſo by the action of the Muſcles which make the Ribs move upwards. The reaſon is that the Ribs cannot move after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner without drawing the Diaphragm by its Extremities, which muſt of neceſſity make it loſe its Convexity.</p>
               <p>We find therefore by the ſearch that we have made into the whole Breaſt, that it is compoſed of certain parts which do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:51501:90"/> the Cavity of it, and of other parts which do diminiſh it. This makes us know ſo evidently the way how the Reſpiration is made, that we cannot almoſt doubt but that it is performed after the manner that we are going to explain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="discourse">
               <head>The eighteenth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the Reſpiration.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE diſtinguiſh two times in Reſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The time of the entry of the Air into the Breaſt, they Name it In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, and the time of its going out, which they call Exſpiration. The Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is made, when the <hi>Subclaviar,</hi> the Great, the two ſmall Teethed, and the Intercoſtal Muſcles do together draw the Ribs upwards The Diaphragm is extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo at the ſame time by the riſing of the Ribs which draw it by its Extremities, and by the Spirits which do then run into its Fibres. So the Cavity of the Breaſt is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:51501:90"/> and the external Air preſſed by the Walls of the Cavity of the Breaſt. It cannot move then but on the ſide where it meets with the leaſt reſiſtance. It finds none at the entry of the Tracheal Artery, and it rencounters every where elſe. There it enters, it gets into the Bronchiae, from hence it paſſes into the Veſicles of the Lungs It blows them up as much as is needful for them to occupy as much ſpace as the Walls of the Breaſt do abandon. Even as the motion which is given to the two Boards of a pair of Bellows when they are raiſed from one another, does thruſt as much Air into the Bellows as is needful to occupy the ſpace which the Boards of the Bellows have left.</p>
               <p>By this means the Muſcles which ſerve to draw down the Ribs have their Fibres extremely ſtretcht to the length. The Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of the Muſculous Tunicle of the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheal Artery and of the Bronchiae, are alſo greatly ſtretcht. Both the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by their ſpring do rebound. The Nerves ſend ſome Spirits into their Cavity.
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:51501:91"/> They are ſhortned. By this Contraction the Ribs are forc'd downward. The Cavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Breaſt is diminiſht, and the Carti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages of the Bronchiae do re-enter into one another. So the Air which the Veſicles of the Lungs did contain is ſo preſt that it goes out. It paſſeth from the Veſicles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Bronchiae, from the Bronchiae into the Tracheal Artery, and from thence out of the Body. And it is this going out of the Air from the Lungs, which is called Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</p>
               <p>Since Reſpiration is no other thing but Inſpiration immediatly followed by Exſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and this Exſpiration followed as quickly by a new Inſpiration, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; we may very well affirm that Reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is made by means of the Muſcles of the Breaſt, of the Diaphragm, of the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Tunicle, of the Tracheal Artery and of the Bronchiae. Theſe Organs act ſucceſſively. And the action of the one hinders the action of the other. From whence we conclude that we may in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon conſider them as Antagoniſt Muſcles.</p>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:51501:91"/>
               <p>All the Blood which paſseth through the right Ventricle of the Heart, goeth from thence into the Lungs, and the Lungs receive the External Air into their Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicles. So we have ground to think that this Air produceth ſome change in the Blood which paſſeth through the Lungs.</p>
               <p>We remark indeed a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Blood which enters into the Lungs, and the Blood which goes out of them. That which enters by the Pulmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Artery is of a Red paſſably deep, whereas that which returns from the Lungs by the Pulmonary Vein is of a bright and fluid Red.</p>
               <p>Behold a very conſiderable change which befals the Blood in paſſing through the Lungs. This change cannot be made but by the Air which blows up their Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicles, and by this means preſſeth the ſmall Arteries, and the ſmall Veins which are ſpread there. This preſſure doth mingle more exactly the Principles of Blood and does oblige it to run more quickly into the branches of the Pulmonary Vein, to go
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:51501:92"/> from thence into the left Ventricle of the Heart.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this exact mixture of the Principles of the Blood and this paſſage from the Arteries into the Veins, is not cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of producing the change that we have remarked; it muſt needs be that ſome Principle of Air extremely ſubtile, mingles with it. This Principle may paſs through the Pores of the Arteries, and inſinuate its ſelf among the parts of the Blood.</p>
               <p>That which makes the thing yet more probable is, that the Blood which is expoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Air acquires a ſurface extremely Red and of a colour like to that of the Blood which comes from the Lungs by the Pulmonary Vein. By which we ſee that the Air produces in the Blood a bright and florid Red by being mingled with it.</p>
               <p>Since therefore the Air does produce this effect, we cannot in reaſon doubt, that the change of colour which befals the Blood in paſſing through the Lungs, comes from the Air which ſwells its Veſicles.</p>
               <p>All the difference which is between the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:51501:92"/> Blood of the Veins and that of the Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, is the ſame with that of the Blood which enters into the Lungs, and of that which comes from them. So we may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirm that this difference is made in the Lungs and not in the Ventricles of the Heart, where the Blood does not receive any alteration. For if you take Blood out of the <hi>Vena Cava,</hi> and afterwards out of the Pulmonary Artery, you ſhall find no difference between theſe two Bloods. Nevertheleſs that which is taken out of the Pulmonary Artery has paſt through the right Ventricle of the Heart. After this if you take of the Blood of the Pulmonary Vein and afterwards of the Aorta, you ſhall ſee that theſe two Bloods are alike in all things, though the one has been taken at its entrie into the left Ventricle of the Heart, and the other at its going out.</p>
               <p>It remains as yet to examine what are the principles of Air which produce the change that the Blood contracts in paſſing through the Lungs. When we conſider the Air narrowly We find amongſt many
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:51501:93"/> principles which compoſe it a Nitrous Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſpread through all its Maſs. There are in Phyſick and Chymie a prodigious num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Experiments, which render the thing certain. And becauſe the Spirit of Nitre does produce in the Blood the ſame change with the Air, we have ground to think that the change which the Air makes in the Blood as it paſſes through the Lungs, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the Nitrous Spirit of the Air its mingling with it.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of Nitre is compoſed of Acids and Alcalies. The Alcalies do rarifie the Sulphurs of the Blood, and the Acids fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with its Volatile Alcalies. The Blood becomes thereby more ſubtile, more agitated and more ratified.</p>
               <p>From all this we may conclude that the Reſpiration ſerves to make the Blood paſs from the Pulmonary Artery into the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monary Vein, and to keep up the fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it by means of the Nitrous Spirit which mingles its ſelf with it. And ſince this Spirit heightens the Red colour of the Blood, it may be alſo ſaid that the Reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:51501:93"/> ſerves to maintain it, and that by its means the Lympha and Chyle which do mingle with it, take by degrees its Colour and Nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="discourse">
               <head>The ninteenth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the Spleen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen we follow the Blood, which goes out of the left Ventricle of the Heart, we find that the firſt Entrail, of thoſe which we have not yet examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to which it goes, is the Spleen. It is of a red Colour, of a conſiderable big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, plac'd in the lower Belly, on the left ſide, and a little lower than the Liver.</p>
               <p>In the Spleen there is an Artery and a Nerve, which do enter into it in Company, and a Vein which goes out at the ſame place. Theſe Arteries end in little Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branous Cells, whoſe Figure does nearly reſemble the Leaf of the Fearn. The Vein derives its Origine from the ſame Cells.
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:51501:94"/> This appears when we blow into the Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or the Vein, for the Breath paſſeth into the Cells.</p>
               <p>Theſe Cells are all filled with ſmall Glandules heaped upon one another, like the Raiſins of a Cluſter of Grapes. Theſe Glandules receive ſmall Branches of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries from the Trunck of the Splenical Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and Nervous Filaments from the Nerve which enters with the Artery into the Spleen. From each heap of theſe Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules there goes a root of a Vein, which being united together, do compoſe the Splenick Vein.</p>
               <p>On the Surface of the Spleen we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive many Lymphatick Veſſels, which do empty their Lympha into Pecquet's Reſeſvatory.</p>
               <p>By all that we have ſaid, it appears, that nothing enters into the Spleen, but the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Spirits which come by the Nerves, and the Blood which comes thither by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries. There goes nothing out alſo but the Lympha which runs by the Lympha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Veſſels into the Reſervatory of the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:51501:94"/> Chyle, and the Blood which goes by the Splenical Vein. The Lympha is nothing but the Remains of the Nutritive Juyce of the Spleen, and it appears not to have any other quality in this place, than what it has every where elſe. As for the Blood, it has the ſame colour and conſiſtence which we obſerve in other Veins</p>
               <p>Theſe Obſervations do extremely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex us as to the uſe of the Spleen. For if the Arteries do bring unto it Blood, it may be ſaid, that this is but to nouriſh it, and if the Nerves do bring thither Animal Spirits, this is but to give unto the Nutritive Juyce, the fluidity that is needful So that we find nothing yet but what ſimply ſerves to the Nouriſhment of this part.</p>
               <p>Yet we cannot ſay that it is entirely uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. For what appearance is there that an uſeleſs part ſhould alwayes be found in the Animal Body, ever of the ſame frame and in the ſame ſituation Nature, it is like, would not have been ſo exact in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if it ſerved for nothing So that it is probable it has in the Animal Occonomy ſome uſe which we do not know.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:51501:95"/>
               <p>But for that on ſuch occaſions we muſt be ſatisfied with conjectures till we find better, we may ſuppoſe that a ferment di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtils from the Veſicles of the Glandules and that it mingles with the Blood which paſſeth through the Spleen. That the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this ferment is ſuch that it diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangleth from the other parts of the Blood, the parts which are proper to compoſe the Bile.</p>
               <p>The reaſon which makes us of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, is that all the Blood which goes from the Spleen paſſes into the <hi>Vena Porta</hi> and from thence goes to the Liver, where we know it rids it ſelfe of thoſe parts which are fitteſt to compoſe the Bile. But this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent, though the moſt probable, has many difficulties.</p>
               <p>All know that an Animal can live many years after the taking out of the Spleen, but this ſayes nothing as to its uſe or Inutility; ſince the cutting out of the Pancreas, whoſe uſes are known and which is acknowledged to be moſt neceſſary for the maintaining of the Animal Oeconomy, does not hinder a Dog from living many years.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="discourse">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:51501:95"/>
               <head>The Twentieth Diſcourſe. <hi>Of the Reins, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>reters.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are in the lower Belly two Bodies made like to French beans plac'd upon the loins, on the two ſides of the deſcending Aorta, and the aſcending <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Cava.</hi> Theſe Bodies receive Arteries from the Aorta, they call them Emulgent Arteries, and they ſend Veins to the <hi>Vena Cava.</hi> They call theſe Veins the Emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Veins. And theſe Bodies are called the Reins.</p>
               <p>We find them firſt wrapt up in a Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle which covers the whole Cavity of the lower Belly. Next to this there is another Tunicle which does immediatly cover them. And in fine, when we have taken off theſe two Tunicles we diſcover the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Reins, upon which we have the pleaſure to obſerve an agreable ramificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sanguineous Veſſels.</p>
               <p>Theſe Sanguineous Veſſels do enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:51501:96"/> the Reins upon there Concave ſide which looks towards the Aorta and the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Cava.</hi> Many ſmall Nerves go from the <hi>Plexus Renalis</hi> and bear them faithful Company. They are all ſhut up in a ſmall Membranous Cover, and the Nerves are loſt in its ſubſtance. Afterwards theſe Veſſels are ſpread through the outer ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Reins and enter into ſmall Glandules, of which this whole outer ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is compoſed.</p>
               <p>Theſe Glandules are faſtned to the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels as the Grapes to the Trunk of the Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. By this means they make ſmall Lobes wrapt up into a particular Tunicle. This Tunicle enters partly into the Capſula, and partly into the Cavity of the Reins, which they call the Baſſin. All theſe ſmall Lobes do adhere to the one or the other of theſe by ſmall Tendinous Filaments.</p>
               <p>From each Glandule there goes an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretory Veſſel They deſcend in a ſtraight line to the Baſſin, being coucht one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide another. When they come near to peirce the Tunicle which makes its inward
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:51501:96"/> Cover, many of them joyn together and make up a great Pipe. This Pipe has an opening by which it communicate with the Baſſine, about which opening we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark a little Riſing, which they call a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilla.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Cavity of the Baſſin is Covered with a very thick Tunicle. It is formed of the Expanſion of the ſmall Pipes which pierce it. It is afterwards ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted towards the Concave ſide of the Reins, that it takes the forme of a Veſſel of the bigneſs of a Gooſe feather. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends in the form of an S. and goes into a Bag, placed in the lower part of the <hi>Abdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> under the Pecton. They call this Bag the Bladder of the Urine.</p>
               <p>Theſe Veſſels they call the Ureters. They are wrapt up in the <hi>Peritonaeum,</hi> and in a proper Tunicle, which communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates with that which does immediately cover the Reins. Their Subſtance is Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branous and very Thick. Their Fibres are ſo variouſly interwoven that they keep no order.</p>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:51501:97"/>
               <p>The uſe of the Reins is to ſeparate a Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Seroſity from the Blood, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from the Glandules into the Baſſins, and from thence runs by the Ureters into the Bladder. This Liquor they call <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="discourse">
               <head>
                  <hi>The twentieth and firſt Diſcourſe.</hi> Of the Bladder, and of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</head>
               <p>THe Bladder is a Bag into which all the Urine goes, which the Reins do ſeparate from the Blood. Its Figure is like to that of a Pear. It is ſo Situated, that its wider part, which they call the Bladder, is alwayes turned upwards, and its more narrow part, which they call the neck of the Bladder, is ever turned down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p>It is held in this Situation by two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Ligaments. The firſt goes from its bottom to the Navel: It hinders it from falling downwards. The ſecond is very ſhort. In Men it keeps it fixt upon the
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:51501:97"/> 
                  <hi>Rectum,</hi> in Women upon the <hi>Matrix,</hi> ſo that the Bladder cannot turn either to the left or right Hand. The firſt is inſerted in its fore part, and the ſecond in its hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part.</p>
               <p>The Bladder is made up of three Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles. The firſt is nothing but a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the <hi>Peritonaeum,</hi> which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraps it outwardly. It is compoſed of Tendinous Fibres variouſly interwoven. The middle Tunicle is made of Carneous Fibres. Of theſe they reckon three Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. The firſt is of ſome great Fibres coucht on the fore-part of the Bladder, which come in a ſtraight line from its bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom even to its neck. The ſecond is of Fibres which do enwrap the Bladder Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly. They may be called Circular Fibres. And the third coucht under the Circular, is of Fibres which croſs the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer obliquely, going from the left to the right Hand, from the bottom of the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der even to its neck. We ſhall call them Tranſverſe Fibres. In fine, the inner Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle is compoſed of Tendinous Fibres, of
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:51501:98"/> ſuch a Textures as has not been yet diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. When the Bladder is not blown up, it is all wrinkled, and within it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes covered with a Mucilage. At the neck of the Bladder there is a Muſcle made of ſtrong and Circular Fibres. It is a <hi>Sphin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter</hi> which keeps it alwayes ſhut.</p>
               <p>From all this we may conclude that the Bladder is a Concave Muſcle, whoſe outer and inner Tunicles are Tendons, and the middle Tunicle, the Belly.</p>
               <p>The Inſertion of the Ureters into the Bladder, ſhewes evidently enough that its uſe is to be the Reſervatory of the Urine, and that all we have remarked in its frame. tends to no other end but to keep the Urine in its Cavity, and to thruſt it forth when it is therewith filled.</p>
               <p>I ſay that the Bladder is the Reſervatory of the Urine, for that the Ureters are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted into its Cavity after ſuch a manner, as that the Urine can eaſily enter there, but cannot return again into the Ureters. They creep for ſome ſpace between the outter and middle Tunicles, afterwards
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:51501:98"/> they peirce the middle Tunicle, and creep a little farther between it and the inner, which they peirce towards the neck of the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. So the Urine can paſs without much difficulty from the Ureters into the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But as the Bladder ſwells by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Urine it ſtraittens the ends of the Ureters which creep amongſt its Tunicles, ſo that the Urine in the Bladder cannot enter there.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sphincter</hi> of the Bladder is the cauſe that the Urine makes ſome ſtay in its Cavity. And leaſt in ſtaying there its ſalts ſhould prick the inner Tunicle, nature has conveyed thither the Mucilage which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noints it on all ſides.</p>
               <p>The Longitudinal Fibres ſhorten the Body of the Bladder when the Animal Spirits do contract them. The Circular and the Tranſverſe do by their action ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it. So when the Fibres are filled with Spirits the Bladder is Leſſened in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. And if then there be Urine in its Cavity, it makes its paſſage maugre the reſiſtance of the <hi>Sphincter,</hi> and gets out
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:51501:99"/> of the Body by a ſmall Pipe which they call the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Pipe is nothing but the Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Inner Tunicle of the Bladder. In Women its opening is in the <hi>Pudendum,</hi> and in Men it extends its ſelf into the Body of the Wand, and terminates in the end of the <hi>Balanus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By all that has been ſaid we ſee that the Reins, the Ureters, the Bladder and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> have been made to ſeparate the Urine from the Blood, and to convey it out of the Body, not only as uſeleſs, but even as hurtful to the maintaining of the Animal Oeconomie.</p>
               <p>To underſtand theſe truths aright, it is to be obſerved that the Urine is almoſt compoſed of nothing but Phlegms and Volatile Salts; having but very little of Sulphur, Earth, and fixt Salt.</p>
               <p>The Nitrous Spirit which mingles with the Blood in the Lungs is compoſed of Acids and Alcalies. Its Acids coming to joyn with the Alcalies of the Blood do make a Salt. And for that the moſt part
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:51501:99"/> of the Alcaline parts of the Blood are Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile, the Salt which is made of them is alſo Volatile. Theſe Volatile Salts might diminiſh the natural Fermentation of the Blood and ſtop its Courſe. To prevent this miſcheif, the Author of Nature has plac'd the Reins into the Bodies of Animals, which do ſeparate theſe Saline parts from the Maſſe of the Blood. And for that alſo a too great abundance of Phlegm, would make the Blood too ſlow and hinder the Spirits from acting, the Reins do not only ſeparate the Salts, but alſo the Phlegms, which are the two Principles whoſe too great abundance would be cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of chocking the ordinary Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Humours, upon which the life of Animals depends.</p>
               <p>Moreover it is remarked that when the Urine abounds in Alcalies, that is to ſay, when its Salts are not ſtrongly charged with Acids, it is thick and troubled. And when it has a deal of Acids, that is, when its Salts are well furniſht with them, it is more clear and Tranſparent. And when there is much
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:51501:100"/> Salt in a little Phlegm, the Urine is of a reddiſh Colour. And when there is much Phlegm and little Salt, it is clear, and is very near unto the ordinary Colour of Water.</p>
               <p>There is remarked in the Urine a little Cloud, which is formed of ſome parts of the Mucilage, which we have ſaid is in the Bladder. The Salts of the Urine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatch them by little and little, and carry them along with them. This Cloud ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears when the Urine begins to cool, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the coolneſs doth condenſe it, and by this mean renders it more viſible.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51501:100"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
